<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The byrth of mankynde, newly translated out of Laten into Englysshe. In the which is entreated of all suche thynges the which chaunce to women in theyr labor, and all suche infyrmitees whiche happen vnto the infantes after they be delyuered. And also at the latter ende or in the thyrde or last boke is entreated of the conception of mankynde, and howe manye wayes it may be letted or furtheryd, with diuers other fruytefull thynges, as doth appere in the table before the booke</title>
            <title>Swangern Frawen und hebammen Rosegarten. English</title>
            <author>Roeslin, Eucharius, d. 1526.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1540</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 191 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 80 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A10887</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 21153</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S116014</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99851231</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99851231</idno>
            <idno type="VID">16499</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A10887)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 16499)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 142:18)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The byrth of mankynde, newly translated out of Laten into Englysshe. In the which is entreated of all suche thynges the which chaunce to women in theyr labor, and all suche infyrmitees whiche happen vnto the infantes after they be delyuered. And also at the latter ende or in the thyrde or last boke is entreated of the conception of mankynde, and howe manye wayes it may be letted or furtheryd, with diuers other fruytefull thynges, as doth appere in the table before the booke</title>
                  <title>Swangern Frawen und hebammen Rosegarten. English</title>
                  <author>Roeslin, Eucharius, d. 1526.</author>
                  <author>Jonas, Richard.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[1], VI-LXXXVIII leaves, [2] leaves of plates   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By T[homas] R[aynald]] Cum priuilegio regali, ad imprimendum solum,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Imprynted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[Anno Domini. M.CCCCC.XL. [1540]]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>By Eucharius Roeslin, whose first name is given on leaf 6v.</note>
                  <note>A translation by Richard Jonas, whose name appears on leaf 6r, of a Latin translation of: Der swangern Frawen und hebammen Rosegarten.</note>
                  <note>Printer's initials and publication date from colophon; printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: AB⁴ C-Y⁴.</note>
                  <note>Variant: title page lacks "Cum priuilegio ..".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Obstetrics --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:16499:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:16499:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>¶ The byrth of Mankynde / newly tranſla<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ted out of Laten into Englyſſhe.</p>
            <p>In the which is entreated of all ſuche thynges the which chaunce to women in theyr labor, and all ſuche infyrmitees whiche happen vnto the Infantes after they be delyuered. And alſo at the latter ende or in the thyrde or laſt boke is entreated of the Conception of mankynde, and howe manye wayes it may be letted or furthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryd, with diuers other fruytefull thynges, as doth appere in the table before the booke.</p>
            <p>¶ Cum priuilegio Regali, ad impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendum ſolum.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:16499:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>¶ An admonicion to the reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Or ſo muche as we haue enterpryſed the interpretation of this preſent boke, offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rynge and dedicatyng it vnto our moſte gracyous and vertuous Quene Kate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryn onely, by it myndyng and tenderyng the vtilite and wealthe of all women, as touchynge the greate parell &amp; dangeours, which moſte commenly oppreſſeth them in theyr paynefull labours. I requyre all ſuche men in the name of God, whiche at any tyme ſhall chaunſe to haue this boke, that they vſe it godlye, and onely to the profet of theyr neyghbours, vtterly eſchuynge all rebawde and vnſemely communi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cacion of any thynges contayned in the ſame, as they wyll anſwere before God, whiche as wytneſſeth Chriſt, wyll requyre a counte of all ydell wordes, and muche more then of all rebawde and vncharitable wordes. Euery thynge, as ſayth Salomon, hath his tyme, and truely that is farre oute of tyme, yea and farre from all good honeſtie, that ſome vſe at the commune tables and without any difference before all companyes rude<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye and leudelye to talke of ſuche thynges, in the which they ought rather to knowe muche, and to ſaye lyttell, but only where it maye do good, magnifyeng the mygh<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tye God of nature in all his workes, compaſſionatynge and pytyenge oure euen Chriſtians, the women whiche ſuſtayne and endure for the tyme ſo greate dolor and payne for the byrth of mankynde and delyue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raunce of the ſame in to the worlde.</p>
            <closer>Prayſe God in all his workes.</closer>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb n="vi" facs="tcp:16499:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>¶ Vnto the moſt gracious / and in all good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe moſt excellent vertuous Lady Quene Katheryne / wyfe and moſt derely belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyd ſpouſe vnto the moſte myghty ſapient Chriſten prynce / Kynge Henry the .viii. Richard Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nas wyſſheth perpetuall ioye and felicyte.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Here as of late (moſte excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent vertuous Quene) many goodly and proper treatyſe / as well concernynge holye ſcripture / wherein is contey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned the onely comforte and conſolacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of all godlye people: as other prophane artes and ſciences ryght neceſſary to be knowen &amp; had in vſe / haue ben by the paynefull dyligence of ſuche clarkes which haue embuſyed them in the ſame very earneſtlye and circumſpect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye ſet forth in this oure wulgare Englyſſhe tunge / to the greate enrytchynge of our mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther langage / and alſo the greate vtilite and profet of all people vſynge the ſame / and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monge all other thynges / oute of the noble ſcyence of Phiſyke haue ben dyuers / proper / 
<pb facs="tcp:16499:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>and profitable matters compyled and tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated from the Laten tunge in to Englyſhe / by the readynge of the whiche ryght manye haue confeſſed them ſelfes to haue receaued greate lyght and knowlege of ſuch thynges in the which they haue founde no ſmal com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>forte and profet. And in this behalfe there is in the Laten ſpeche a boke entytled / depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tu hominis: that is to ſaye / of the byrthe of mankynde / compyled by a famous doctor in Phyſycke / called Eucharius / the whiche he wrote in his owne mother tunge / that is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ynge a Germayn / in the Germayne ſpeche / afterwarde by an other honeſt clarke / at the requeſte and deſyre of his frende tranſpoſed in to Laten: the whiche boke for the ſyngu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar vtilite and profete that enſueth vnto all ſuch as rede it / and moſte ſpetiallye vnto all women (for whoſe onely cauſe it was wryt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten) hathe bene ſythe in the Doutche and Frenche ſpeche ſet forthe and emprynted in greate nomber / ſo that there be fewe matro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes and women in that partes / but (yf they can rede) wyll haue this booke alwayes in readyneſſe: conſyderynge then that the ſame commodite and profet whiche they in theyr
<pb n="vii" facs="tcp:16499:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>regyons do obtayne by enioyng of this lytle boke in theyr maternall langage / myght al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo enſue vnto all wome<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in this noble realme of England / if it be ſet forth in the Englyſhe ſpeche / as concernynge this / I haue done my ſymple endeuoure for the loue of all wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manhode / and chieflye for the moſte bounde ſeruyce / the whiche I owe vnto youre moſte gracyous hyghnes to tranſlate the ſame in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to oure tunge. Moſte humbly deſyryng fyrſt your graces hyghnes / and then conſequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye all noble ladyes and gentylwomen with other honeſte matrones to accepte my pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes and good wyll employd in the ſame: the whiche thynge as I doo not doubte for the woonte and incomperable benignite / good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes / and gentylnes inſet &amp; planted in youre graces nature / ſo ſhall it be no lyttell encour<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ragynge vnto me hereafter with farther de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liberation and paynes to reuyſe and ouerſe the ſame agayne / and with much more dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence / to ſet it forthe. For conſyderynge the manyfolde / daylye / and imminente daun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>georus and parelles / the which all maner of women of what eſtate or degre ſo euer they be in theyr labor do ſuſtayne and abyde: yea
<pb facs="tcp:16499:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>many tymes with parell of theyr lyfe / of the whiche there be to many examples nedeleſſe here to be reherſed. I thought it ſhulde be a very charytable and laudable dede: yea and thankefullye to be accepted of all honorable &amp; other honeſt matrons / yf this lyttell trea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tyſe ſo frutefull and profytable for the ſame purpoſe were made Englyſh / ſo that by that meanes it myght be redde and vnderſtande of them all / for as touchynge mydwyfes / as there be many of them ryght expert / dilige<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t / wyſe / circumſpecte / and tender aboute ſuche buſyneſſe: ſo be there agayne manye mo full vndyſcreate / vnreaſonable / chorleſhe / &amp; farre to ſeke in ſuche thynges / the whiche ſholde chieflye helpe and ſocoure the good women in theyr moſt paynefull labor and thronges. Throughe whoſe rudeneſſe and raſſheneſſe onely I doubte not / but that a greate nom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber are caſte awaye and deſtroyed (the more petye.) For this cauſe and for the honor of almyghty god / and for the moſte bounde ſer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uyce / the which I owe vnto your grace / moſt gracyous and vertuous Quene / I haue iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged my labor &amp; paynes in this behalfe ryght well beſtowed / requyrynge all other women
<pb n="viii" facs="tcp:16499:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>of what eſtate ſo euer they be / whiche ſhall by readynge of the ſame fynde lyght and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forte to yelde and render thankes vnto your moſte gracyous hyghnes / wyſſhyng greate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly that it myght pleaſe all honeſte &amp; mother<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye mydwyfes dylygently to reade and ouer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſe the ſame / of the which althoughe there be many / which do knowe muche more perad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenture / then is here expreſſed / yet am I ſure in the readynge of it / theyr vnderſtandynge ſhall be muche cleared and haue ſome what farther perceueraunce in the ſame. It is no ſmall charge the which they take vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> them / for yf when anye ſtraunge or peryllous caſe doth chanſe / the mydwyfe be ignorant / or to ſeke in ſuche thynges which are to be had in remembraunce in that caſe / then is the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie loſte and vtterlye doth peryſſhe / for lacke of due knowledge requyſite to be had in the mydwyfe. Wherfore I beſeche almyghtye God / that this my ſymple induſtrye and la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bor maye be throughe youre grace vnto the vtilite / wealth / and profet / of all Englyſſhe women / accordynge to my vtter and hartye deſyre and entente / to whome alſo I daylye praye longe to preſerue and proſpere youre
<pb facs="tcp:16499:5"/>moſte gracyous hyghnes bothe to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tynuall comforte &amp; conſolacion of our moſte redoubted &amp; withoute co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>paryſon moſte excellent Chriſten Prynce / and alſo the ioye and gladneſſe of all his louynge ſubiectes.</p>
            <closer>Amen.</closer>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb n="ix" facs="tcp:16499:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <list>
               <head>¶ Here after begynneth the table of this preſente boke.</head>
               <item>¶ After what maner and faſſhyon the byrthe lyeth in the mothers wombe, &amp; howe many caules it is co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſed and wrapped in. Cap .i. fol .xi.</item>
               <item>¶ Of the tyme of byrth, &amp; which is called naturall or vnnaturall. Ca .ii. fol .xiii.</item>
               <item>¶ Of eaſye, and vneaſye, difficull, or dolorous dely<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, and the cauſes of it, with the ſygnes howe to knowe, and foreſe the ſame Cap .iii. fol .xiui.</item>
               <item>¶ Howe a woman with chylde ſhall vſe her ſelfe, &amp; what remedies be for them that haue harde labour. Cap .iiii. fol .xvii.</item>
               <item>¶ Remedyes and medici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes by the which the labor maye be made more tolle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> eaſye, and without great payne. Ca .v. fo .xxv.</item>
               <item>¶ Certayne pylles y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che make the labor eaſye &amp; without payne. fol .xxvii.</item>
               <item>¶ Howe the ſecondyne or ſeconde byrth ſhall be ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to yſſue forth, if it come not frely of his owne kynd Cap .vi. fol .xxviii.</item>
               <item>¶ Howe that many thyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges chaunſe to the women after theyr labor, and howe to auoyde, defende, or to re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>medye the ſame. Cap .vii. fol .xxxii.</item>
               <item>¶ Of aborcementes or vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tymelye byrthes, and the cauſes of it, and by what remedyes it maye be defen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ded, holpen and eaſed. Cap .viii. fol .xli.</item>
               <item>¶ Of deade byrthes, and by what ſygnes or tokens it maye be knowen, and by what meanes it maye alſo be expelled. Ca .ix. fo .xlvii.</item>
               <item>¶ Howe the infant newly borne, muſte be handled, nouryſhed, and loked to. Cap .x. fol .liii.</item>
               <item>¶ Of the nourſe, and her mylke, and howe longe the chyld ſhold ſoucke. fo .lv.</item>
            </list>
            <pb facs="tcp:16499:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <list>
               <head>¶ The Table of the ſeconde boke.</head>
               <item>¶ Of diuers diſeaſes and infirmities which chaunſe to chyldren lately borne, &amp; y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> remedyes therfore. fo .lix.</item>
               <item>¶ Of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> flyx or ouermoche looſeneſſe of the bely. fo .lx.</item>
               <item>¶ To vnlooſe the chylde beyng boudnen. fo .lxii.</item>
               <item>¶ Remedye for the cra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pe or diſtention of the mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bres. fol .lxiii.</item>
               <item>¶ Remedie for the cough and dyſtyllatyon of the heade. fol .lxiii.</item>
               <item>¶ Remedye for ſhorte wynde, fol .lxv.</item>
               <item>¶ Agaynſte wheles or bladders on the tounge. fol .lxv.</item>
               <item>¶ Of exulceration or clef<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ture, chappynge, or chyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyng of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mouth. fol .lxvi.</item>
               <item>¶ Of Apoſtumation and runnyng of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> eares .lxvii.</item>
               <item>¶ Of Appoſtumation in the heade. fol .lxvii.</item>
               <item>¶ Of the ſwellyng or bol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyng of the eyes. fol .lxvii.</item>
               <item>¶ Of the ſcum or whyte of the eye. fol .lxvii.</item>
               <item>¶ Agaynſte immoderate heate or the feuer. fo .lxvii.</item>
               <item>¶ Agaynſte frettynge or knawynge in the bellye. fol .lxviii.</item>
               <item>¶ Agaynſte ſwellynge of the body. fol .lxviii.</item>
               <item>¶ Agaynſte often ſnee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſynge. fol .lxviii.</item>
               <item>¶ Of whelkes in the body and the cure. fol .lxix.</item>
               <item>¶ Agaynſte ſwellynge of the coddes. fol .lxix.</item>
               <item>¶ Agaynſte ſwellynge of the nauyll. fol .lxx.</item>
               <item>¶ Agaynſte vnſlewyneſſe fol .lxx.</item>
               <item>¶ Agaynſt yeryng. fo .lxxi</item>
               <item>¶ Of yerkeneſſe or appe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyte to vomyte. fol .lxxi.</item>
               <item>¶ Agaynſt fearful and ter<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rible dreames. fol .lxxii.</item>
               <item>¶ Agaynſte the mother. fol .lxxiii.</item>
               <item>¶ Of ſhorte brethe, horſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, or whyſtelynge in the throte. fol .lxxiii.</item>
               <item>¶ Agaynſte tenaſmus. fol .lxxiiii.</item>
               <item>¶ Agaynſt wormes in the belly. fol .lxxiiii.</item>
               <pb n="x" facs="tcp:16499:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <item>¶ Of chawfynge or gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lynge in any place of the body. fol .lxxv.</item>
               <item>¶ Of the fallynge ſycke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. fol .lxxvi.</item>
               <item>¶ Conſumptyon or py<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nynge awaye of the bodye. fol .lxxvii.</item>
               <item>¶ Of laſſytude, weryneſſe or heuyneſſe of the chyldes bodye. fol .lxxvii.</item>
               <item>¶ Of trymblynge of the body, and the membres of the bodye. fol .lxxviii.</item>
               <item>¶ Of the ſtone. fo .lxxviii.</item>
               <item>¶ Of google eyes, or lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kynge a ſquynt. fo .lxxviii.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>¶ The Table of the thyrde booke.</head>
               <item>¶ Of ſuche thynges the whiche ſhalbe entreated of in this thyrde booke. Cap .i. fol .lxxix.</item>
               <item>¶ Of conceptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and how many wayes it maye be hyndered or letted. Ca .ii. fol .lxxx.</item>
               <item>¶ Howe many wayes con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cepcyon maye be letted, &amp; howe the cauſes maye be knowen. Cap .iii. fol .lxxxi.</item>
               <item>¶ Howe to know whether lacke of conception be of the woman or of the man, and howe it maye be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaued whether ſhe be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaued or no. Cap .iiii. fol .lxxxiii.</item>
               <item>¶ Of certayne remedyes and medycynes whiche ſhall cauſe the wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man to conceaue. Cap .v. fol .lxxxv,</item>
            </list>
            <trailer>¶ Here endeth the table of this booke,</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="authors_foreword">
            <pb facs="tcp:16499:7"/>
            <p>¶ For bycauſe that in this booke many ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes be founde certayne meaſure &amp; waygh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes of phyſyke not knowen peraduenture to all ſuche as ſhal chaunce to reade it / therfore here brefly I haue ſet them furthe / ſhowyng the value and eſtimation of them ſo far as ſhall be requyſite to the better vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dynge of ſuche thynges the whiche ye ſhall reade in the ſame treatyſe.</p>
            <list>
               <item>The pownde wayght xii. ownces.</item>
               <item>The ownce contayneth viii. drammes.</item>
               <item>The dramme iii. ſcruples</item>
               <item>The ſcruple xx, graynes,</item>
            </list>
            <p>¶ Where as is written that the ſcruple con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayneth .xx. graynes / ye muſte note that by theſe graynes be vnderſtande graynes of barley taken out of the myddell of the eare / of the whiche .xx. maketh a ſcruple: ſo that the pownde contayneth .v. M .vii. C .lxii. graynes. &amp;c. as folowyth.</p>
            <list>
               <item>The pownde v. M .vii. C .lxii. graynes.</item>
               <item>The ounce contayneth iiii. C .lxxx. graynes.</item>
               <item>The dramme lx. graynes.</item>
               <item>The ſcruple xx. graynes.</item>
            </list>
            <pb n="xi" facs="tcp:16499:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>¶ ye ſhall alſo note here that many tymes ye ſhall happen vppon ſtraunge names of ſuche thynges the whiche are occupyed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boute infyrmytees ſpoken of in this booke / for the whiche there is no englyſhe but are vſyd in there owne proper names of greke or laten: and they are ſuche for the mooſte parte whiche are to be had onely at the Apo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thecaries / beyng of them ryght wel knowen wherfore when ye ſhal nede any ſuch thyng yf ye ſende the ſame names in your byll to the apothecaries they wyll ſoone ſpede your purpoſe: neyther do this yf ye maye without the aduiſe of ſome experte and well ler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned phyſytiane.</p>
            <trailer>¶ Here after begynneth the fyrſte booke.</trailer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div n="1" type="book">
            <pb facs="tcp:16499:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>THE FYRSTE BOKE.</head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>THE FYRSTE</hi> ¶ After what maner and faſſhyon the byrthe lyethe in the mothers wombe, and howe many caules it is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſed and wrapped in. ¶ Cap .i.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N ſo muche as oure entent is in this boke folowynge to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treate and ſpeake of the byrthe of mankynde / and of ſuche thynges whiche happen and chaunſe to the mother in her labor and tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uayle / in the deliueraunce of the ſame / it ſhal be fyrſt verye neceſſary to ſhewe after what maner and faſſhyon the infant lyeth in the mothers wombe / and in howe many cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les the ſame is lapped and wrapped: to the farther knowlege and perceuerance of ſuche thynges the whiche we ſhall entreate of hereafter.</p>
               <p>¶ wherfore ye ſhall vnderſtande that the byrth lyeth in the mother after this maner: Fyrſte it lyeth rownde in maner as a bowle the handes beynge betwene the knees / and the hedde lenyng on the knees: eyther of the eyes ioynynge vppon eyther of the knees: the ryghte eye vppon the ryghte knee: and
<pb n="xii" facs="tcp:16499:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>the lefte vpon the lefte / the nooſe dependyng betwene the knees / ſo that the face and fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parte of the infante is towarde the inwarde partes of the woman / lyenge in maner vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryght in the mothers matryce.</p>
               <p>¶ Farther ye muſte vnderſtande that there be thre coueres or caules in the whiche the byrthe is contayned and lapped: of the whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che the one compaſſyth &amp; embraſyth rownd aboute the byrthe / and the other two caules alſo: and it is called the ſecondyne ſeconde byrth or the after byrthe: the whiche defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth the byrthe frome noyſum and yll hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours encreaſynge in the matryce after con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ception by retenſyon of the flowres other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wyſe wonte to paſſe and yſſue furthe ones in the monethe / the whiche yll humours yf they ſholde touche or come nere to the byrth wolde greatlye peryſhe and hurte the ſame. But after the deliueraunce of the pryncipall byrth theſe humours alſo with the foreſayd caule or ſecondyne yſſue furthe / and is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the after byrthe.</p>
               <p>¶ The ſeconde caule with the whiche the byrth is coueryd / compaſſeth the ſame byrth frome the nauyll downe warde / couerynge
<pb facs="tcp:16499:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>all the inferyour partes of the infant / and this ſkynne or caule is as it were fulle of plyghtes and wrynkles: and through this caule the byrthe is defended and kepte from yll and ſharpe humours as vryne or pyſſe yſſuynge frome the infante and ſwette. &amp;c. for ſo longe as the chylde is in the mothers wombe it ſendeth furthe vrine / not by the due membres but by the vayne whiche pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedeth out of the nauell.</p>
               <p>¶ The thyrde ſhynne or caule lykewyſe con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tayneth all the byrthe in it defendynge alſo the ſame frome humours &amp; vryne: and from the boyſteſnes of the ſecondyne or fyrſt caule and this is called the armoure or defence of the byrthe.</p>
               <p>¶ This is the maner of the ſytuation and lodgyng of the infante in the mothers bellye: and theſe be the thre caules contaynynge and encloſyng in the byrth. Nowe wyll we ſpeake of the tyme of byrthe.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <pb n="xiii" facs="tcp:16499:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <head>¶ Of the tyme of byrthe, and whiche is called naturall or vnnaturall. ¶ Cap .ii.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Nd when the tyme of byrthe ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prochyth nere / moſte commenly theſe ſygnes folowyng come be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore: by the which the tyme of la<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bor is knowen to be at hande.</p>
               <p>¶ Fyrſte certayne dolours and paynes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gynne to growe about the guttes / the nauell / and in the raynes of the backe / and lykewyſe aboute the thyghes &amp; the other places beinge nere to the priuy partes / which lykewyſe then beginneth to ſwell and to burne and to expell humours / ſo that it gyueth playne and eui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent token that the labor is nere.</p>
               <p>¶ But ye ſhall note that there is two man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of byrthes / the one called naturall / the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther contrarye to nature. Naturall byrthe is when the chylde is borne bothe in due ſeaſon &amp; alſo in due faſhion. The due ſeaſon is moſt commenlye after the .ix. moneth or aboute .xl. wekes after the conception / althoughe ſome be delyuered ſometymes in the ſeuenthe mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth / and the chylde proueth verye well. But ſuch as are borne in the eyght moneth / other
<pb facs="tcp:16499:10" rendition="simple:additions"/>they be dead before the byrth / or els lyue not longe after / as the noble medicine Auicenna doth teſtifye.</p>
               <p>¶ The due faſhion of byrthe is this / accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dynge as wytneſſeth Albert the greate / fyrſte the head commeth forwarde / then foloweth the necke and ſhouldes / the armes with the handes lyenge cloſe to the bodye towarde the fete / the face and forepart of the chylde beyng towardes the face and foreparte of the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther / as it appeareth in the fyrſte of the byrthe fygures. For as Albertus writeth / and as we haue reherſed before alſo / before the tyme of delyueraunce the chylde lyeth in the mothers wombe the face and breſte beynge towardes the backe of the mother / but when it ſholde be delyuered / it is torned clene contrary / the head downewarde / the fete vpwarde / and the face towarde the mothers bellye / and that yf the byrth be natural. Another thyng alſo is this / that yf the byrthe be naturall / the delyuerance is eaſye withoute longe taryenge or lokynge for it.</p>
               <p>¶ The byrth contrarye to nature is / when the mother is delyuered before her tyme / or oute of due ſeaſon / or after any other faſhion
<pb n="xiiii" facs="tcp:16499:10" rendition="simple:additions"/>then is here ſpecyfyed before / as when bothe legges procede fyrſte / or one alone / with both the handes vp / or both downe / other elles the one vp &amp; the other downe / and diuers other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe as ſhalbe hereafter more clerely declared</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <head>¶ Of eaſye, and vneaſye, difficull, or dolorous delyueraunce, and the cauſes of it, with the ſygues howe to knowe, and foreſe the ſame. ¶ Cap .iii.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">V</seg>Ery many be the parelles / dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous &amp; ſtronges which chanſe to women in theyr labor / whiche enſue &amp; come in dyuers wayes / &amp; for dyuers cauſes / ſuch as I ſhal here declare.</p>
               <p>¶ Fyrſt when the woman that laboreth is conceyued ouer yonge / as before .xii. yee or .xv. yere of aege / which cha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſeth ſomtyme / though not verye often / and that the paſſage be ouer anguſt ſtreate or naro we / other naturally / or els for ſome diſeaſe and infirmite / which may happen about that parte / as apoſtumes / puſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhes / pyles / or blyſterres / and ſuch other / tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowe the whiche cauſes nature can not (but with great dolor and payne) open and dilate
<pb facs="tcp:16499:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>it ſelfe to the expellynge &amp; delyuerance of the chylde. And ſometyme the veſyke or bladder / or other intralles beyng about the matrice or wombe be alſo apoſtumat &amp; blyſtered / whiche beynge greaued / the matrice or wombe lyke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wyſe is greaued with them / and that hynde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth greatly the deliueraunce. Alſo ſometyme in the fundament are emerrodes or pyles and other puſſhes / chappynges or chynnes which cauſe greate payne / alſo hardnes and difficul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te or byndynge of the belly / which thinges for the grefe and payne that enſueth of them cau<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſeth the woman to haue lyttell power to help herſelfe in her labor.</p>
               <p>¶ Farthermore if the partie be weke and of feble complexion / or of nature very colde / or to yonge / or very aged / or to groſſe and fatte / or contrarye wyſe to ſpare and leane / or that ſhe neuer had chylde before / or that ſhe be ouer ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morous and fearefull / dyuers waywarde / or ſuche one as wyll not be ruled / remouyng her ſelfe from one place to another / all ſuch thyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges cauſeth the labour to be much more payn full / cruell / and dolorous / then it wolde other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wyſe be. Alſo ye muſt vnderſtande that gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rallye the byrthe of the man is eaſyer then the
<pb n="xv" facs="tcp:16499:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>byrth of the female.</p>
               <p>¶ Item yf the chylde be of a fuller &amp; greater groweth than that it maye eaſelye paſſe that narowe paſſage / or contrarye wyſe / yf it be ſo faynt / weake / and tender / that it can not turne it ſelfe / or doth it very ſlowly / or yf the woma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> haue two chyldren at ones / other elles that it with the which ſhe laboreth be a menſter / as for example / yf it haue but one body and two heddes / as appeareth in the .xvij. of the byrth fygures / ſuch as of late was ſene in the domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of werdenberghe.</p>
               <p>¶ Agayne whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it procedeth not in due tyme or after due faſhion / as when it cometh forthe with bothe fete or both knees togyther / or els with one fote onely / or with both fete downe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde and both handes vpwarde / other els (the which is moſt perellous) ſydelong / arſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longe / or backelonge / other hauynge two at a byrth / both procede with their fete fyrſt / or one with his fete and the other with his head / by thoſe and diuers other wayes the woman ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteyneth greate doloure payne and anguyſh.</p>
               <p>¶ Item yf the woman ſuffer aborſme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t / that is to ſaye brynge forth her chylde in the .iiii. or v. moneth after the conception / whiche is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb facs="tcp:16499:12" rendition="simple:additions"/>the due tyme / in this caſe it ſhalbe great payne to her / for ſo muche as (accordynge to Galenus ſayenge) in that tyme the entrance of the wombe is ſo firmely and ſtrongely en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cloſed / that ſcace the poynte of a nedle maye enter in at it.</p>
               <p>¶ Alſo yf the chyld be dead in the mothers bellye it is a verye perellous thynge / forſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muche as it can not be eaſely turned / nother can it weld or helpe it ſelf to come forth / or yf the chyld be ſycke or weakened / ſo that it can not for feableneſſe helpe it ſelfe. The whiche thynge maye be foreſene &amp; knowen by theſe tokens: Yf the woman with chylde haue ben longe ſycke before her labor / yf ſhe haue ben ſore laxed / yf after her conception ſhe haue had dayly &amp; vnwontly her flowres / yf ſtreate after one moneth vppon the conception her breſtes yelde anye mylke / yf the chylde ſteare not ne moue at ſuche tyme as is conuenient for it: theſe be tokens that it ſholde be verye weake. By what tokens ye ſhall knowe it is dead / I ſhall ſhewe you in the nynth chapter hereafter.</p>
               <p>¶ Alſo there is greate parell in laborynge / when the ſecondyne or latter byrthe is ouer
<pb n="xvi" facs="tcp:16499:12" rendition="simple:additions"/>fyrme or ſtronge / and wyll not ſone ryue or breake aſunder / ſo that the chylde maye haue his eaſy commyng forth. And contrary wyſe when it is ouer weake ſlender or thynne / ſo that it breaketh aſunder before that the chyld be turned or apte to yſſue forthe / for then the humours which are collecte and gathered to gether about this ſecondyne or ſecoſide byrth paſſe away ſoner then it ſholde do / &amp; the byrth ſhall lacke his due humidite and moyſtenes / whiche ſholde cauſe it the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ſelyar to procede and with leſſe payne.</p>
               <p>¶ The byrth alſo is hindered by ouer much colde or ouer muche heete / for in ouer muche colde the paſſage and all other powres of the laborynge woman be coarted and made nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rower then they wolde otherwyſe be. Lyke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wyſe ouer much heate debiliteth / weakeneth and faynteth both the woman and the chyld / ſo that neyther of them in that caſe can well welde or helpe them ſelfes for fayntneſſe.</p>
               <p>¶ And forther yf the woman haue vſed to eate commenly ſuch meate or fruytes / whiche do exiccat or drye and conſtrayne or bynde / as medlars / cheſtenuttes / all ſowre fruyte / as trabbes / chokeperes / and ſuche other / with
<pb facs="tcp:16499:13" rendition="simple:additions"/>ouer muche vſe of vergers / &amp; ſuch lyke ſowre ſauces / with ryſe myll / and many other thyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges / all this ſhall greately hynder the byrth.</p>
               <p>¶ Alſo the vſe of colde bathes after the .v. moneth folowyng the conception or to bathe in ſuch water where alome is / yron / or ſalte / or any ſuche thynges which do coarcte and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrayne / or yf ſhe haue ben oftentymes heauye and murnyng / or yll at eaſe / or yf ſhe haue ben kept ouer hungrye and thurſtye / or haue vſed ouer much watche and walkinge / other yf ſhe vſed a lyttell before her labor thinges of great odour ſmell or ſauoure / for ſuche thynges at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracte and drawe vp warde the mother or ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trice / the whiche is greate hynderaunce to the byrthe.</p>
               <p>¶ Alſo yf the woma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> fele payne onely in the backe and aboue the nauell and not vnder / it is ſygne of harde labor / lykewyſe yf ſhe ware wont to be delyuered with greate payne in ty<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mes paſſed / is a ſygne of great labor alwayes in the byrth.</p>
               <p>¶ Nowe ſygnes and tokens of an expedite and eaſy delyueraunce be ſuch as be contrary to all thoſe that go before. As for example / when the woman hathe ben wonte in tymes
<pb facs="tcp:16499:13" rendition="simple:additions"/>paſſed eaſelye to be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> that in her labor ſhe feale but lyttell thronge or dolor / or thoughe ſhe haue greate paynes / yet they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mayne not alwayes in the vppar partes / but deſcend to the nether partes or botome of the bellye.</p>
               <p>¶ And to be ſhorte in all paynefull &amp; trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleſome labours / theſe ſygnes betoke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fy good ſpede and lucke in the labor: vnquiet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes / muche ſtearynge of the chylde in the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers belly / all the thronges and paynes tom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blynge in the fore parte of the botome of the bellye / and when the woman is ſtronge and myghtye of nature / and ſuch as can well and ſtrongelye helpe her ſelfe to the expellynge of the byrth. And agayne euell ſygnes be thoſe / when ſhe ſwetethe colde ſwete: and that her pulces beate and labor ouer ſore / and that ſhe her ſelfe in the laborynge faynt and ſwowne: theſe be vnluckye and mortall ſygnes.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <head>¶ Howe a woman with chylde ſhall uſe herſelfe, and what remedies be fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> them that haue harde labor. ¶ Cap .iiii.</head>
               <pb facs="tcp:16499:14" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſuch as are in ſuche difficull parell of labor / as we haue ſpoken of before / ye muſt obſerue / kepe &amp; marke thoſe thynges whiche we ſhall (by the grace of god) ſhew you in this chapter folow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ynge. Fyrſt the woman with chyld muſt kepe two dyettes / the one a monethe before her la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bor / the other in the verye laborynge / &amp; aboue all thynges ſhe muſte exchue and forbare all ſuche thynges which maye hynder the byrthe ſo nere as ſhe can poſſible / the which we reher<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſed in the chapter before / but yf there be anye ſuche thynge which can not be auoyded / for ſo much as it commeth by nature or by long con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tynuance and cuſtome: in this caſe yet ye ſhall vſe ſome ſuch remedies / the which maye ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what aſſwage it / mollifye it / or make it more eaſye or tollerable / ſo that it hynder the byrth ſo muche the leſſe.</p>
               <p>¶ But yf it ſo be / that any infirmitie or dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeaſe / ſwellyng / or other apoſtumation chanſe about the mother or the preuy parte / or about the veſyke or bladder / as the ſtone / the ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gurye / and ſuche lyke: the whiche thynges may cauſe ſuche ſtrayteneſſe and coarctation
<pb n="xviii" facs="tcp:16499:14" rendition="simple:additions"/>that vnnethe greate and horrible payne / the partie can be delyuered or diſcharged: in theſe caſes it behouethe ſuche thynges to be loked vnto and cured before the tyme of labor com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>methe / by the aduyſe of ſome experte Sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion.</p>
               <p>¶ Alſo yf the woman be ouer muche conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pat / or bounde all wayes / ſhe muſte vſe the monethe before her labour ſuche thynges / the whiche maye lemfye / mollifye / diſſolue / and looſe the bellye: as aples fryed with ſugre ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken faſtynge in the mornynge / and after that a draughte of pure wyne alone / or elles tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pered with the iuyce of ſwete and rype ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples. Alſo to eate fygges in the mornynge faſtynge and at nyghte / looſethe welle the bellye.</p>
               <p>¶ Agayne in this caſe ſhe muſte refrayne frome all ſuche thynges as doo harden / re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraynt / and conſtipat: as be ſuche thynges / the whyche be browled or roſted / &amp; ryſe / harde egges and myll / and ſuche lyke.</p>
               <p>¶ Alſo yf farther neceſſite require ſhe maye receaue a clyſter / but it muſte be very gentell and eaſye tempered other with cheken brothe or brothe of other fleſſhe: ſhe maye vſe alſo
<pb facs="tcp:16499:15" rendition="simple:additions"/>ſome other eaſye and temperat purgation to mollifye and looſe her with all: alſo a ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitar tempered with ſope / larde / or the yolke of egges.</p>
               <p>¶ And yf it chaunſe that (the labor draw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ynge nere) ſhe waxe faynte or ſyckelye: then muſte ye comforte her with good comfortable meate / drynke / holſome and noble electuaries / and in this tyme muſt ſhe do all ſuch thinges the whiche can make her apte and ſufficiente to her labor / &amp; to vſe ſuche thynges the which maye laxe / open / and mollifye the nature and paſſage / ſo that the byrth maye the more frely procede: and that chieflye in the younger wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men. The elder women for becauſe that / that partes in them be ſomewhat dryer &amp; harder / therfore they muſte vſe hote and moyſt thyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges which haue properte to lenifye and ſople / and that bothe in meate and drynke / and alſo in outwarde fomentations / bathynges / ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitaries and anoyntme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes: Anoyntmentes wherewith ye maye ſople the priuie place / be theſe: hennes greſe / duckes greſe / gooſe greſe / alſo oyle olyfe / or lyneſede oyle / or oyle of fene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greke / or the viſcoſite of holyoke &amp; ſuch other / and for drinke let her vſe good type wyne mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>xed
<pb n="xix" facs="tcp:16499:15" rendition="simple:additions"/>with water: alſo ther muſt be a conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in the dietynge of the woman / that ſhe maye vſe ſuch thynges the which maye moy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſten her / and not make her fatte. Contrarye-wyſe let her auoyde ſuch thynges the whiche ſholde exiccat drye conſtrayne or coarte her: &amp; that all the monethe before her labor. But a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout .x. dayes before the tyme (yf ſhe fele any payne or grefe) let her vſe euery day to waſhe or bathe her with warme water / in the which alſo that ſhe tary not ouer longe in bathynge for weakening of her: in the bath let her ſtand ſo chat the water come aboue the nauell a lyt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tell / and lette be ſodde in the water mallows / holyoke / camomell / mercurye / maydenhere / lyneſede / fenegreke ſede / and ſuch other thyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges which haue vertue to mollifye and ſuple: and yf it ſo be that for weakeneſſe of the body ſhe maye not endure this bathynge in warme water / then with a ſponge or other cloth dyp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped in the foreſayde bathe / let her ſokynglye waſhe her fete / her thyghs / and her pryuy par<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes / the whiche thynge ſhall greatly profet to her. But in ſuche tyme beware ye come not in the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mune hote houſes / for they wolde cauſe you to be feble and faynte / whiche ware yll in
<pb facs="tcp:16499:16"/>this caſe.</p>
               <p>¶ And when ye are thus bathed or waſhed / then ſhall it be very conuenient for you to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noynte with the foreſayde greſes and oyles youre backe / belly / nauell / ſydes / and ſuch pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces as are nere to the preuy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e partes. Farther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more it ſhall be greatelye profitable for her to conueye inwarde in to the preuye parte theſe foreſayde oyles or greſes with a ſponge or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thynge made for the purpoſe / ſhe lyenge vpryght the middes of her body moſt hyeſt / ſo that it maye the better remayne within her / and that chieflye / yf the matrice be drye / other elles the partie very leane and ſpare.</p>
               <p>¶ It ſhalbe alſo verye profytable for her to ſuffume the nether places with muſke / am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bre / gallia muſcata / whiche putte on embers yelde a goodlye ſauour / by the whiche the ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther places ope<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelfe &amp; draw downwarde.</p>
               <p>¶ Alſo as I ſayd before / ſhe muſt take good hede to her dyette / that ſhe take thynges the whiche maye comforte and ſtrenghten the bo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dye / feadynge not ouer muche of any thynge / and to drynke pleaſaunt and well ſauerynge wyne / or other drynke / alſo moderatly to exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyce the body in doyng ſome thing / ſtearynge / mouinge / goyng / or
<pb n="xx" facs="tcp:16499:16"/>ſtandyng / more then other wiſe ſhe was wo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to do: theſe thinges farther the byrth &amp; make it the eaſyer: &amp; this is the ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ner of dyette the which we aduiſe the woman to kepe the moneth before her labor or longer.</p>
               <p>¶ Another dyette there is / the whiche ſhe ought to obſerue in the tyme of labor / when the ſtormes and thronges begyn to come on / and the humours / whiche yet hytherto haue remayned about the matrice or mother collec<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ted / nowe begyn to flowe forth: and this ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of dyette conſyſteth in two ſortes. Fyrſte that ſuche thynges be procured and had in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyneſſe whiche maye cauſe the byrth or labor to be very eaſye. Secondly to withſtande / de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fende &amp; to put awaye ſo nere as may be the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t &amp; preſent dolours. And as touchinge this poynt / it ſhalbe very profitable for her for the ſpace of an houre to ſyt ſtyll / the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ryſyng again to go vp &amp; downe a payre of ſtayres cryeng or reaching ſo loude as ſhe ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / ſo to ſtere herſelfe.</p>
               <p>¶ Alſo it ſhalbe very good for a tyme to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne and kepe in her brethe / for becauſe that thorow that meanes the guttes and intralles be thruſt to gether and depreſſed downeward. Alſo it ſhalbe verye good to receyue the ſame
<pb facs="tcp:16499:17" rendition="simple:additions"/>medicine / the which we ſhall deſcribe hereaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter / for that medicine expellethe and ſendeth forthe the byrth.</p>
               <p>¶ But when the woma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> perceaueth the ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>trice or mother to waxe laxe or looſe / and to be dyſſolued / and that the humours yſſue forthe in great plente / then ſhall it be mete for her to ſyt downe lenynge backewarde in maner vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryght. For the which purpoſe in ſome regio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s (as in France and Germanye) the mydwyfes haue ſtooles for the purpoſe / whiche beynge but lowe and not hye frome the grounde / is made ſoo compaſe wyſe and caue or holowe in the myddes / that that maye be receaued from vndernethe whiche is loked for: and the backe of the ſtoole lenyng backewarde / recea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uethe the backe of the woman / the faſhion of the which ſtole is ſet in the begynninge of the byrth ſygures hereafter.</p>
               <p>¶ And when the tyme of labor is come / in the ſame ſtole ought to be put manye clothes or clowtes in the backe of it / the whiche the midwife may remoue fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> one ſyde to another accordyng as neceſſite ſhal require. The myd<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wyfe herſelfe ſhall ſyt before the laboryng wo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>man / and ſhall diligently obſerut and wayte
<pb n="xxi" facs="tcp:16499:17" rendition="simple:additions"/>howe muche &amp; after what maner the chylde ſtearethe it ſelfe: alſo ſhall with her handes fyrſte annoynted with the oyle of almondes or the oyle of whyte lylies rule &amp; directe eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry thynge / as ſhall ſeme beſt. Alſo the myd<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wyfe muſte enſtructe and comfort the partie not onely refreſſhynge her with good meate and drynke / but alſo with ſwete wordes / ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uynge her good hope of a ſpedefull delyue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raunce / encouragyng and enſtomacking her to pacience and tolleraunce / byddyng her to holde in her brethe in ſo muche as ſhe maye / alſo ſtrekynge gentylly with her handes her belly aboue the nauel / for that helpeth to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe the byrth downewarde.</p>
               <p>¶ But and yf the woman be any thynge groſſe / fat / or fleſſhly it ſhall be beſt for her to lye grouelyng / for by that menes the matrice is thruſt and depreſſed downe warde / anoyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tynge alſo the preuy partes with the oyle of whyte lyllies. And yf neceſſite require it / let not the mydwyfe be afrayde ne aſſhamed to handle the places and to relaxe and loſe the ſtraytes / for ſo muche as ſhall lye in her / for that ſhall helpe wel to the more expedite and quycke labor.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:16499:18"/>
               <p>¶ But this muſt the mydwyfe aboue all thynges take hede of that ſhe co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pell not the woman to labor / before the byrth come fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde / &amp; ſhewe it ſelfe. For before that tyme all labor is in vayne / labor as muche as ye lyſt. And in this caſe many tymes it cometh to paſſe / that the partie hath labored ſo ſore before the tyme / that when ſhe ſholde labor in dede / her myght and ſtrength is ſpent be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in vaine / ſo that ſhe is not nowe able to helpe her ſelfe / and that is a peryllous caſe.</p>
               <p>¶ Farthermore when the ſecondine or ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conde byrthe (in the which the byrth is wrap<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ped and conteyned) doth ones appeare / then maye ye knowe that the labor is at hande / wherfore yf the ſame ſecondine breake not of his owne kynde / it ſhalbe the myd wyfes parte and offyce with her nayles eaſely and gentely to breake it / and rent it / or yf it maye not ſo conuenientlye be done / then reyſe vp betwene your fyngers a pece of it / and cutte it of with a payre of ſheeres / or a ſharpe knyfe / but ſoo that ye hurte not the byrthe with the cutte / this done / by and by enſueth conſeque<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly the flux and flowe of humours / of the whyche I ſpake before / and then
<pb n="xxii" facs="tcp:16499:18" rendition="simple:additions"/>nexte foloweth immediatly the byrthe.</p>
               <p>¶ But yf it ſo chanſe the ſecondine ſholde be cutte by the mydwyfe and all the watery parte yſhued and ſpent before due tyme and neceſſite ſholde requyre it / ſo that the preuye paſſage be leſt exiccat and drye / the byrth not yet appearynge / and by this meanes the la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bor ſholde be hyndered and letted. In this caſe ye ſhall annoynt and mollify that preuy paſſage with the oyle of white lillies / or ſom of the greſes ſpoken of before / fyrſte whar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med and ſo conueyed in to the preuy partes the whiche thynges wyll cauſe the waye to be ſlypperye / ſople / and eaſye for the byrth to paſſe. But chiefly in this difficulties ſholde profette the whyte of an egge to gether with the yolke powred in to that ſame place / whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che ſholde cauſe it to be moſte ſlypperye and ſlydynge.</p>
               <p>¶ And yf it ſo be / that the byrthe be of a greate groweth / and the head ſtycke in the commynge forthe / then muſte the mydwyfe helpe al that ſhe may / with her handes fyrſt annoynted with ſome oyle openyng and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>largynge the waye / that the yſſue maye be be the frear: lykewyſe muſte be done yf ſhe
<pb facs="tcp:16499:19"/>bare two chyldren at once. And all this is ſpoken of the naturall byrth when that fyrſt procedeth the head / and then the reſte of the body ordinatly / as ye mayeſe in the fyrſte of the byrth fygures folowynge.</p>
               <p>¶ ij. But when the byrthe commeth con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarye to nature / then muſt the mydwyfe do all her diligence and payne / yf it may be poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible / to turne the byrthe tenderlye with her annoynted handes / ſo that it maye be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced agayne to a naturall byrthe / as for example: Some tyme it chanſeth the chylde to come the legges and both arines and han<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>des downewarde clooſe to the ſydes fyrſte forthe / as appearethe in the ſeconde of the byrth figures / in this caſe the mydwife muſt do all her payne with tender handelyng and annoyntyng to receaue forthe the chylde / the legges beynge ſtyll cloſe to gether / &amp; the han<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>des lykewyſe remaynynge / as appeareth in the ſay<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e .ij. figure. Howe be it / it were farre better (yf it maye be by any meanes) that the mydwyfe ſholde turne theſe legges co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>myng fyrſte forthe vpwardes agayne by the belly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde / ſoo that the heade myghte deſcende downward by the backe part of the wombe
<pb n="xxiii" facs="tcp:16499:19"/>for then naturally agayne &amp; without parell as the fyrſte myght it procede &amp; come forthe.</p>
               <p>¶ iii. Agayne ſometyme the byrthe com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth forth with both legges and fete fyrſte / the handes beinge lyfted vp aboue the head of the chylde / and this is the parellouſt ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of byrth / that is as appeareth in the iij. of the byrth figures. And here muſt the myd wyfe do what ſhe maye to turne the byrth yf it maye be poſſible to the fyrſt figure / and yf it wyll not be / muſte reduce the handes of it downe to the ſides / &amp; ſo to reduce it into the ij. figure. But yf this alſo wyll not be: then receaue the feate as they come forth / &amp; binde them with ſome fayre lynnen clothe / and ſo tenderly and very ſoftly looſe out the byrth tyll all be come forth / and this is a very <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pardous labor.</p>
               <p>¶ iiij. Alſo ſometyme the byrth commeth forwarde with one fore onely / the other be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ynge left vpwarde / as appeareth in the .iiij. fygure. And in this caſe it behoueth the la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borynge woman to laye her vpryght vppon her backe / holdynge vp her thyghes &amp; belly / ſo that her heade be the lower part of her bo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dy: then let the mydwyfe with her hande re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne
<pb facs="tcp:16499:20" rendition="simple:additions"/>in agayne the fore that commeth oute fyrſte in as tender manner as maye be / and warne the woma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that laboreth to ſtere and moue her ſelfe / ſo that by the mouynge and ſterynge the byrth maye be turned the head downewarde / and ſo to make a naturall byrth of it / and then to ſet the woman in the ſtole agayne / and to do as ye dyd in the fyrſte fygure / but yf it ſo be that notwithſtandyng the mothers ſtearynge and mouynge the byrth do not torne / then muſte the mydwyfe with her hande ſoftelye fetche out the other legge whiche remayned behynde / euermore takynge hede of this that by handelynge of the chylde ſhe do not remoue ne ſette oute of theyr place the two ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des hangyng downe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde towarde the fete.</p>
               <p>¶ v. Lykewiſe ſomtyme it co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth to paſſe that the ſyde of the chyld co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth forwarde / as appeareth in the .v. fygure / &amp; then muſt the mydwyfe do ſo / that it maye be returned to his naturall faſſhion / &amp; ſo to come forthe.</p>
               <p>¶ vi. Alſo ſometyme the chylde commeth forthe the fete forwarde / the legges beynge abroade / as in the .vi. figure / and then muſte the mydwyfe ſe / that the fete &amp; legges maye
<pb n="xxiiii" facs="tcp:16499:20"/>be ioyned to gether / and ſo to procede &amp; come forth / euer more regarding the handes / as I warned you before.</p>
               <p>¶ vij. Yf it come with one of the knees or bothe forewarde / as in the .vij. figure / then muſte the mydwyfe putte vp the byrth / tyll ſuch tyme as the legges and fete come ryght forth / and then to do as afore.</p>
               <p>¶ viij. When the chylde commeth hed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longe / one of the handes commyng out and appearyng before / as in the .viij. figure / then let the byrthe procede no farther / but let the mydwyfe put in her hande and tenderlye by the ſhoulders thruſt in the byrth agayne / ſo that the hande maye be ſetteled in his place agayne &amp; the byrth to come forth ordinatly &amp; naturally / as in the firſt figure / but if by this meanes the hand come not to his conuenie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t place / then let the woman lye vpryght with her thyghes &amp; bellye vpwardes / &amp; her head downewardes / ſo that by that meanes it maye be brought to paſſe / and then to bryng her to her ſeate agayne.</p>
               <p>¶ ix. But yf it procede with both handes forewardes / then muſte ye lykewyſe do as a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore: by the ſhulders thruſtynge it backe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gayne
<pb facs="tcp:16499:21"/>/ vntyll ſuche tyme as the handes lye cloſe to the ſydes / and ſo to come forth as ap<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>peareth in the .ix. fygure.</p>
               <p>¶ x. But when it commeth arſewarde / as in the .x. fygure maye be ſene / then muſte the mydwyfe with her handes retorne it a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gayne / vntyl ſuch tyme that the byrth be tur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ned / the legges and fete forwarde / otherels yf it maye ſo be / it ware beſte that the heade myght come forwarde / and ſo naturallye to procede.</p>
               <p>¶ xi. And yf it ſo be that it appere &amp; come forth fyrſt with the ſholders / as in the .xi. fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gure / then muſt ye fayre and ſoftely thruſt it backe agayne by the ſholders / tyll ſuch tyme as the heade come forewarde.</p>
               <p>¶ xii. But when the byrth co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth forthe with both handes and bothe fete at once / as in the .xij. fygure / then muſte the mydwyfe tenderly take the chylde by the head / and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne the legges vpwarde / and ſo to receyue it forth.</p>
               <p>¶ xiij. And when it cometh breſtewarde / as in the .xiij. figure / the legges and handes bydynge behynd / then let the mydwyfe take it by the fete or by the head / which that ſhall
<pb n="xxv" facs="tcp:16499:21"/>be moſte apte and commodious to come for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde / returnynge the reſt vpwarde / and ſo to receaue it forth / but if it maye be hedlong / it ſhalbe beſt.</p>
               <p>¶ xiiij. Nowe ſometyme it chaunſeth the woman to haue two at a burden / and that bothe procede to gether headlonge / as in the xiiij. figure / &amp; then muſt the midwyfe receue the one after the other / but ſo that ſhe let not ſlyppe the one whyleſt ſhe taketh the fyrſte.</p>
               <p>¶ xv. Yf bothe come forthe at once with theyr fete foreward / then muſt the mydwyfe be very diligent to receaue fyrſt the one / and then the other / as hath ben ſhewed before.</p>
               <p>¶ xvi. When the one co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth hedlonge / the other fotewyſe / then muſt the mydwyfe helpe the byrth that is moſt nereſt the yſſue / &amp; it that co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth fotelo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g (if ſhe ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>) to returne it vpon the head / as is ſpoken of before / ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king euer the hede / that the one be not noyſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to the other i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> receauing forth of ether of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</p>
               <p>¶ And to be ſhorte / let the mydwyfe often tymes annoynte and mollifye the waye and paſſage with ſome of the foreſayd oyntmen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes / to make the womans labor ſo much the eaſyar / &amp; haue the leſſe thronge trauell and
<pb facs="tcp:16499:22" rendition="simple:additions"/>payne / &amp; yf there chanſe to be any apoſtume / or dyſeaſe about that places in this tyme by ſuche annoyntynge to alaye and ſwage the payne: ſo that for the tyme it may be the leſſe grefe to the partie / as I poke of before alſo / and for them that be in this caſe / it ſhall be beſt to lye growelyng / as I ſaid of the groſſe fatte and fleſſhly woman.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <head>¶ Remedies and Medicines by the whiche the labor maye be made more tollerable, eaſy, and without great payne. ¶ Cap .v.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Ll ſuche thynges as helpe the byrth &amp; make it more eaſye / are thoſe: Fyrſt the woma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boreth muſt other ſyt grouling or els vpryght leanynge backe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde / accordynge as it ſhall ſeme commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious and neceſſarye to the partie / or as ſhe is accuſtomed. And in wynter or colde whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the chamber wherin ſhe laboreth muſte be warmed / but in ſomer or hote whether / let in the ayre to refreſſhe her withall / leſt be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>twene extreme heate and labor the woman faynt and ſounde / and farthermore ſhe muſt
<pb n="xxvi" facs="tcp:16499:22"/>be prouoked to ſneeſynge / &amp; that other with the powder of Eleborus / or elles of pepper. Alſo the ſydes of the woman muſt be ſtreke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> downewarde with the handes / which thing helpeth greately and farthereth / and let the mydwyfe alway be very diligent prouidyng and ſeinge what ſhalbe neceſſary for the wo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>man / annoyntinge the priuities with oyle or other ſuch greſe as I ſpoke of before in this faſſhion: Take the oyle of whyte lyllies or duckes greſe / &amp; with that temper two gray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes wayghte of Safran and one grayne of muſke / and with that oyntmente annoynte the ſecrete partes. Yf this profet nothynge / then vſe this ſuffumigation.</p>
               <p>¶ Take myrrhe / galbanum / caſtorium / let thoſe be beten and make lyke pylles of them tempered to gether with bulles gaule / then take a dramme of this pylles / and put it on hote coles / and let the woman receaue the fume and ſauoure of it vndernethe.</p>
               <p>¶ Another perfume: Take yelowe brym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtone / myrrhe / mader / galbanum / oppopona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cum / of eche lyke much / and temper all theſe to gether / makynge of them pylles / and with thoſe alſo ye may make fume to be receaued
<pb facs="tcp:16499:23" rendition="simple:additions"/>vnderneth. Ite<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the fume of culuer dunge or of hawkes dunge by puttyng to of oppopo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacum / is ſouerayne for the ſame. All theſe fumes open the poores benethe / and cauſeth nature to be the frear in delyueraunce.</p>
               <p>¶ Alſo it is very good to dyp wooll in the iuyce of rue / and the ſame to conuey into the ſecreates. Alſo the pouder of ariſtolochia ro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>da / or the rote called bothor martis / or ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum terre / or the ſede of ſtaphiſagre: any of theſe wrapped in wooll and conueyed in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde prouoketh &amp; calleth forthe the byrth.</p>
               <p>¶ Item take heleborus / oppoponacu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / and wrap them to gether in wooll / and miniſtre them inwarde: for that wyll brynge forthe &amp; prouoke the byrthe / whether it be alyue or dead. Alſo the rynde and barke of caſſia fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtula beaten to pouder / and tempered with wyne and dronke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / prouoketh well the byrth.</p>
               <p>¶ Item aſa fetida of the bygnes &amp; waight of a peſe myngled to gether with caſtorium of the wayght of a dram<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: beaten to gether &amp; tempered with wyne myxt with water and ſo dronke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / is very good to prouoke the byrth Alſo canell dronke with wine is very good.</p>
               <p>¶ Item take a ſcruple of roſes / with the
<pb n="xxvii" facs="tcp:16499:23" rendition="simple:additions"/>water of the ſede of fenegreke / cicercula / may denhere / all beaten to gether and ſoden / and the oyle of blewe flowre de luce a ſmal quan<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tite tempered there with all: and then geue it to the woman that laboreth / and it ſhall prouoke the byrthe greately. Alſo caſſia lig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nea and aſa fetida dronke with wyne / be ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry good for the ſame. Alſo holyoke ſoden in water and dronke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / is ſouerayn for the ſame purpoſe / &amp; it is verye good for her to waſhe her in the water / in the whiche this holyoke is decocte and ſoden in.</p>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>¶ Certayne pylles the whiche make the labor eaſye and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oute payne.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Ake canell or cinamome and of ſauyne of eche a dram<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / of caſſia lignea a dram<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and a halfe / of myrrhe / ariſtolochia rotunda / &amp; coſtemary of eche a dram<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / of ſto<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rax liquida halfe a dram<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / and of oppium the wayght of .xij. graynes / bete theſe all to ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther / and forme them into pylles / and geue vnto the woman two dram<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of theſe pylles with .ij. ounces of good olde wyne.</p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:16499:24" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <p>¶ Item Safrane and Syler Montanum prouoketh the byrth of any lyuynge thynge / yf it be droncke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: howe be it to a woman geue neuer paſſynge a drame at once of Safrane / for greater quantite ſholde greately hurte.</p>
                  <p>¶ Item take .v. drames of Sauyne / of rue or herbe grace one dragm<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; an halfe / of iuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per byryes .ij. dram<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s / of aſa fetida / amonia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cum / madder / of ech .ij. dram<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s: of theſe make pylles / geuen to the woma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in labor with wa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter in the whiche is ſoden ſauyne and peny<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ryall / or els with the brothe of cicercula / and the iuyce of rue ſhall helpe very greately.</p>
                  <p>¶ Item take .ij. dram<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of ſauyne / of aſa fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tida / armoniacum / &amp; madder / of eche halfe a dram<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / theſe temper to gether in pilles / and geue her with wyne .ij. dram<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of the ſame.</p>
                  <p>¶ Item take of ariſtolochia longa / pepper and myrrhe / of eche lyke much / confict them to gether with wyne &amp; make pylles of them / &amp; miniſter them with an ounce of water of the decoction of lupynes / theſe pylles be of ſuch efficacy and ſtrength that it alleuiateth and vnpayneth the byrthe / it delyuereth the matrice or mother from all maner of byrth / be it alyue or dead.</p>
                  <pb n="xxviii" facs="tcp:16499:24" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <p>¶ Item take of whyte bedellium / myrrhe / and ſauyne / of eche lyke much: temper theſe with caſſia lignea and hony / and make pyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les of them of the byggeneſſe of peſen / &amp; of theſe pylles geue at eche tyme .v. to the labo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer / whiche be of the ſame myght &amp; ſtrength with the other pylles ſpoken of here nexte before.</p>
                  <p>¶ Item take of myrrhe / caſtorium / and ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rax / of eche one dram<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / temper them with ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny / and make pylles of it / theſe for this pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe excell and paſſe al other / they be of ſuch vertue and ſtrength in operation.</p>
                  <p>¶ A plaſter to prouoke the byrthe: Take wyld goward / &amp; ſeth it in water / in the ſame water temper myrrhe / the iuyce of rue / and barlye meale / ſo muche as ſhalbe ſufficient / ſtampe theſe thynges to gether / and make it plaſterwyſe / then laye it to the womans belly betwene the nauel and the nether part this plaſter ſhall helpe meruelouſlye.</p>
                  <p>¶ And although many other thinges ther be the which haue vertue and power to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoke byrth and to help it / yet leuyng all ſuch thynges for breuite and ſhorteneſſe we haue ſet here ſuche thynges / which are chiefe and
<pb facs="tcp:16499:25" rendition="simple:additions"/>moſt principally conducent for the ſame pur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>poſe.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <head>¶ Howe the Secondyne or ſeconde byrth ſhall be ſorſed to yſſue forth, yf it come not frelye of his owne kynde. ¶ Cap .vi.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Ere alſo ſomtyme it cometh to paſſe / that the Secondine / whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che is wonte to come to gether with the byrth / remayne &amp; tary behynde and folowe not. And that for dyuers cauſes / one is: For becauſe peraduenture the woman hathe ben ſo ſore weakened and feblyſſhed with trauell / do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour / and payne / of that fyrſt byrth / that ſhe hathe no ſtrength remaynynge to helpe her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe to the expellynge of this ſeconde byrth / another maye be / that it be entangled / tyed / or let within the matrice / which cha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſeth ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny tymes / or that it be deſtitute of humours / ſo that the water be flowen fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it ſoner then it ſholde / which ſhold make the places more ſlyppery and more eaſye to paſſe thorowe / or els that the places ouer weryed with longe &amp; ſore labor / for payne co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tract or gather toge<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther / &amp; encloſe themſelfe agayne / or that the
<pb n="xxix" facs="tcp:16499:25" rendition="simple:additions"/>places be ſwollen for anguyſſhe and payne / and ſo let the comminge forth of the ſeconde byrthe.</p>
               <p>¶ But to be ſhorte of what ſo euer cauſe it be thus ſtopped / the mydwyfe in anye wyſe muſt fynde ſuch meanes that it maye be vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>looſed and expulſed. For otherwyſe greate inconuemency ſholde chaunſe to the partie / and ſpeciallye ſuffocation &amp; chokynge of the matrice / whiche alſo muſt ſo much the more be take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hede to / for becauſe the ſeconde byrth retayned &amp; kept within / wyll ſone putrifye &amp; rot: whereof wyll enſue yll noyſom and pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtiferous vapours / aſcendynge to the harte / the braynes / and the mydryffe / throughe the which meanes the woma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhalbe ſhort wyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded / faynt harted / often ſoundynge &amp; lyenge without any maner of mouynge or ſtearing in the pulces: yee and many tymes is playn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſuffocated / ſtrangled / and dead of it: wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore that none of theſe thinges happen / with all diligens and payne it muſte be prouyded that the ſecondyne be expelled.</p>
               <p>¶ Yf retention of it come by weakeneſſe of the laborer throughe long trauell / then muſt ſhe be recomforted and ſtre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gthed with good
<pb facs="tcp:16499:26" rendition="simple:additions"/>co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fortable meates &amp; drynkes which may en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>harte her / as brothe made of the yolke of eg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges / or with good olde wyne &amp; good fat and tydy fleſſhe / or byrdes / hennes fleſſhe / capon / partrige / pyginnes / and ſuche lyke.</p>
               <p>¶ And yf retentio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of this ſecondine come / becauſe the place is co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tract to gether agayn / otherelles that the matrice is ſwollen for longe payne / then muſt be vſed ſuch thinges to prouoke it oute / the whiche do make the way ſlypper / ſople / and eaſy for it to procede / with the oyles or oyntementes ſpoken of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore / as oyle of whyte lyllies / of maiora<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / and of blewe lyllies. Item the beryes of iumper or galbanum beaten to powder and dronke with luke warmed wyne / wyll cauſe the ſame to yſſue out. Ite<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſothernwood / or elles penyryall ſoden in wyne / and the decoction dronken / is of the ſame vertue.</p>
               <p>¶ Item to ſuffume the ſecreates with the perfumes wrytten of before / is good for this purpoſe / &amp; the fume of the water / in whiche mallous holyoke / and berefutte vt ſoden in / receaued beneth / is lyke good. Alſo to waſhe that partes i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> water in which is ſode<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> branne / or to holde a lyttell bagfull of ſoden branne
<pb n="xxx" facs="tcp:16499:26" rendition="simple:additions"/>to the place / and therewythall to ſooke the place / is very profytable.</p>
               <p>¶ But yf the retention of the ſecondyne come by reaſon that it is entanglyd or faſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in ſome place of the matrice / ſo that it wyl not reſolue ne loſe then make a fume vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>derneth of brymſtone / yuie leues / and creſſes or elles of creſſes and fygges.</p>
               <p>¶ Alſo of all odoriferous and ſwete ſmel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lynge thynges: as ambre / muſke / franken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſe / gallia muſcata and confection nere / the whiche ſauoures and perfumes put on the emberres muſt be ſo cloſely receaued vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dernethe / that no part of the ſmell do aſcend to the noſe of the woman. For to the noſe ſholde the ſauour of nothynge come / but on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye of ſuche thynges / the whyche ſtynke or haue abhominable ſmell: as aſa fetida / caſto rium / mans here or womans here burnt / pecockes fethers burnt. Item in this caſe it ſhalbe very good to make a perfume vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth of the houe of an aſſe / which thinges al<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thoughe they be of yll ſauoure / yet they be of ſuch nature &amp; efficacie / that they occaſionat not onely the ſeco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dine / but alſo dead byrthes to procede &amp; come forth out of the matrice.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:16499:27" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <p>¶ And in this caſe alſo let the woma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with holde her brethe in warde in ſo muche as ſhe can / for that ſhall dryue downewarde ſuche thynges as be in the bodyr to be expelled. Item let her be prouoked to ſneeſe with the pouder of eleborus or pepper put in the noſe holdynge her mouthe and noſe ſoo clooſe as maye be.</p>
               <p>¶ Alſo the oyntment / whiche is called vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guentum Baſilicon / conueyed into the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trice / is very good / for it mollifyeth the place and draweth out the ſecondine parforce / the whiche ſo ſoone as it is expelled / infude the oyle of rooſes in to the ſame matrice. Item rooſewater tempered with a quantite of the pouder of holyoke / and dronke / is good to ex<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pell the ſecondine.</p>
               <p>¶ And yf it be ſo that any parte of the ſecon<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dine do appeare / let the mydwyfe receaue it tenderlye / looſynge it oute fayre and ſoftely leſte it breake / and yf ye doubte that it wyll breake / then let the mydwyfe tye that parte of the whiche ſhe hathe handfaſt to the wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans legge or fote / not very ſtrayght / leſte it breake / nether very lax / leſt it ſlyp in agayne / and then cauſe her to ſneſe. Then yf the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condine
<pb n="xxxi" facs="tcp:16499:27" rendition="simple:additions"/>tarye or ſtycke / ſo that it come not quyckly forewarde / then looſe it a lyttell &amp; a lyttell very tenderlye wrething it frome one ſyde to another / tyll ſuch tyme as it be gotte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> oute / but euer beware of violent and haſtye mouyng of it / leſt that with the ſecond byrth ye remoue the matrice alſo.</p>
               <p>¶ And yf in this meane whyle the women faynt or ſowne by reaſone of great payne en<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſuynge of the takynge a waye of this ſecon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dine / then muſte ye miniſter ſuch thinges to her the which comfort the head and the hart as be electuaries whiche are conficte with muſke / ambre / and the confectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of precious ſtones / as Diamargariton / and ſuche other. Alſo ſuche thynges the whiche comforte the ſtomacke / as Diagalanga / Dia cinamomu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / and ſuch other which are alwaye in a readi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe at the apothecaries / the which thinges ſhe ſhall receaue with wyne.</p>
               <p>¶ Item to remoue the ſecondine and to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel it: take rue / horehownd / Sothernewood / and motherwort / of ethe lyke quantite / and then take ſo muche of the oyle of lyſhes / as maye be ſufficient to ſtype / moyſten and ſoke the foreſayd herbes in / put all this to gether
<pb facs="tcp:16499:28" rendition="simple:additions"/>into a glaſed potte couered with ſuche a co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer that it haue a lyttell hole or vent aboue in the toppe of it / then ſet this pot ouer the fyre of coles / ſo that it boyle a whyle / then take it frome the fyre / and ſette it vnder the ſtole where the woman ſytteth made for the nonce hauyng a pype made for that purpoſe of the whiche the one ende ye ſhall put into the vent or hole of the couer to the pot &amp; the other ende muſt the partie receaue in to her bodye. And ſo to ſyt clooſed rounde aboute with clothes / that no vapoure or ayre go forth of the potte hauing a fewe coles vnder it / to kepe it hote / and thus ſytte the ſpace of an houre or two / tyll ſuch tyme as the ſecon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyne moue and begynne to procede of his owne kynde. And yf it be ſo that ye profette not this wayes / yet then laye this plaſter on the bellye betwene the nauell and the ſecrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes / of the whiche we ſhall ſpeake hereafter / the whiche is of ſuche operation and effica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cite that it expelleth deade byrthes: yf for all this the ſecondyne come not forewarde / then leaue it / and vſe no more medicines ne reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies to that purpoſe but let it alone / for with in fewe dayes it wyll putrifye and corrupte / 
<pb n="xxxii" facs="tcp:16499:28" rendition="simple:additions"/>and dyſſolue into a watery ſubſtance / thycke lyke bryne / or other fex myxed with water / &amp; ſo yſſue forthe. Howheit in the meane whyle it wyll put the woman to great payne in the heade / in the harte / the ſtomacke / as we tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thed before.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <head>¶ Howe that many thynges chaunſe to the women after theyr labor, and howe to auoyde, defende, or to remedye the ſame. ¶ Cap .vii.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is alſo to be vnderſtanded / that many tymes after the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyueraunce happeneth to wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men other the feuer or ague / or ſwellyng or inflation of the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dye / other tumblynge in the belly / or els com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>motion or ſettelynge out of order of the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther or matrice. Cauſe of the which thynges is ſomtymes lacke of due and ſufficient pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation and clenſyng of the flowres after the byrthe / or elles contrarye wyſe ouer muche flowinge of the ſame / whiche ſore doth wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken the woman. Alſo the greate labor and ſtearynge of the matrice in the byrth.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:16499:29" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <p>¶ Then as ofte as it commeth for lacke of due purgation of the flowres / then muſte be miniſtred ſuch thinges / the which maye pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uoke the ſame / whether it be by medicines taken at the mouth / or by lotyon &amp; waſhyng of the fete / or by fumes or odours or empla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration / or by decoction of herbes ſeruynge to that purpoſe / other els by oyntmentes / &amp; ſuche other thynges / accordynge as the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſone or the parell doth requyre / of the which thynges fewe or no wemen be ignoraunt. And ye muſte take diligent hede that ſhe be exactly and vtterly purged: to this be agrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble all ſuche thynges / the whyche prouoke vryne &amp; open the vaynes / making free waye for the bloude to paſſe / &amp; ſende the humours and matter downewarde / as motherworte / azure / ſauyne / penyryall / parcelye / cheruyll / anyſe ſede / fenel ſede / iumper byries / rue / bay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byries / germaunder / valeriane / tyme / cino<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mome / ſpykenarde / &amp; ſuche other. All thoſe thynges as they do prouoke and cauſe vrine ſo do they alſo prouoke and cauſe the flow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res to depart. Howbeit as nere as ye can vſe none of theſe thynges without the counſell of an expert phyſiſyon / leſte whyleſt ye helpe
<pb n="xxxiii" facs="tcp:16499:29" rendition="simple:additions"/>one place ye hurt another / alſo to ſneeſe hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peth muche in this matter / &amp; to holde in the brethe encloſynge the nooſe and the mouth. Alſo fumigation made of the yes of ſalt fyſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhes / or of the houe of a horſe vnderneth / pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uoketh the flowres. Yf ye profet not by this meanes then yf ſhe be able to bare it / let her bloude in the vayne / called Saphena / vnder the ancles of the fete / for this ꝓuoketh flow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res chieflye of all other thynges.</p>
               <p>¶ Lykewyſe doo / yf the woman haue the ague after her labor / for that co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth of lyke cauſe by retention of the flowres / and in the feuer let her vſe to drynke water / in the whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che is decocte barlye beaten / or cicer and bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye to gether / or water in whiche be ſoden Tamaryndi / or waye of mylke / and lette her eate cullys made of a cocke / and ſwete pome Granates: for theſe thynges do prouoke the flowres / &amp; mitigateth the immoderat heate / refreſſhynge greatelye the bodye / looſynge and openynge ſuche thinges / the whiche be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ware conſtricte and cluddered to gether.</p>
               <p>¶ Yf the body after labor do ſwel &amp; inflate then let her drynke water in the which is ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den cicer and cummyn beaten to gether.
<pb facs="tcp:16499:30" rendition="simple:additions"/>Item good olde wyne with the electuarium called diamarte / or the whiche is called alca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kengi: of the whiche Auicenna ſpeaketh in his .v. boke. Item gumme ſerapine / organ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie / and maſticke. Alſo in this caſe a glyſter made of ſuche thynges / the which do vayn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſhe and expelle ventoſitees and wynde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe / alſo a peſſarie or ſuppoſitar made for that parte of Ariſtolochia rotunda / ſquinan tum / ſtorax liquida / doronicum / zeduaria.</p>
               <p>¶ Agayne yf the woman after her labor haue frettynge and knawyng of the guttes / and payne of the matrice and other ſecreate partes there aboute / then let her vſe the va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pour and fume of ſuche thynges the whiche haue vertue to mitigate ſwage and alay the payn / as mallowes / holyoke / fenegreke / cum<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>myn / camomell / ſauyne / and hemlocke.</p>
               <p>¶ Alſo to annoynt the places with oleum ſeſaminum / or with oyle of ſwete almondes And yf no greate heate do abou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de in the wo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>man / ſhe maye drynke tryacle or trifera ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gna with wyne in whiche is decoct mother<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wort or muggeworke.</p>
               <p>¶ Alſo agaynſte paynes in the preuy par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes / take penyriall / policaria / ſyx leues of bay
<pb n="xxxiiii" facs="tcp:16499:30" rendition="simple:additions"/>tree: ſethe them to gether / and receaue the va<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pour vndernethe cloſely. Item take rue / red motherworte / ſothernwood / bete them to ge<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther / and temper them with the oyle of peny ryall / and put all to gether into a pot / and ſet it ouer the fyre a whyle / tyll it be ſomewhat ſoden to gether / and then take it of agayne / &amp; put it all in to a lyttell rounde lynnen bagge made for the purpoſe / the whiche with this herbes in it ye ſhall co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uaye into the ſecretes.</p>
               <p>¶ Item take camomell &amp; lyne of eche lyke much .iiij. handefulles: braye them to gether &amp; ſethe them with whyte wyne / &amp; then put it in a rounde bagge of lynnen / as before was done / &amp; conuey it into the woma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s preuy par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes. Ite<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> let her drynke for the ſame purpoſe ij. graynes of muſke with wyne. ¶ Ite<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> take white onyons &amp; couer the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnder the hote aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhes the which whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they be wel roſted / beate the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to gether with freſhe butter vnſalted / &amp; make it in maner of a plaſter / &amp; then put it in a lynne<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> bag / &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uey itin to the places / as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore / in the meane whyle perfumyng the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uy partes with whyte fra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>kencenſe &amp; ſtorax.</p>
               <p>¶ Yf it be ſo that the woma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> be vexed about the backe and loynes after her labor / take ca<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>momell
<pb facs="tcp:16499:31" rendition="simple:additions"/>/ and muggewoort / of eche .ij. hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulles of woorwode / ſothernewood of eche one handefull / of motherwort .iij. handeful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les / of cinamome and nutmegges bete<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſmall halfe an ounce / decocte all theſe thynges to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether / and in the water of this decoction beynge warme / dyp a ſpunge or other lyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nen clothes fomentynge / ſokynge / and ſtre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kynge the backe with the ſame / and ſo do of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten tymes / or els put all theſe foreſayde her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bes to gether ſoden in a bagge / and laye it plaſterwyſe to the backe.</p>
               <p>¶ Yf this profette not: take oyle nardine / oyle of whyte lyllies / of ech an ounce and an halfe / to the whiche put a dram<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of nutmeg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges beaten to ſmall powder / with this an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noynte the backe. Item take oyle of anys / oyle of camomell / of eche an ounce / oyle of whyte lyllies .ij. ounces / of waxe .ij. dram<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s: diſſolue all theſe to gether ouer the fyre / and there with annoynt the backe.</p>
               <p>¶ But yf after the labor the flowres yſſue more vehementlye &amp; in greater aboundance then they ſholde / to the great effeablyſſhyng of the woman and inducynge of muche lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gor and paynefulnes: then ſyrſt ſhall ye note
<pb n="xxxv" facs="tcp:16499:31" rendition="simple:additions"/>where vpon it co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth: for the cauſe knowen the dyſeaſe maye the more readelye be recu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red: and cauſes of it be dyuers: but moſte eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petiall thoſe that folowe / that is to ſaye: Of muche aboundant ſuperfluous bloude con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayned in the hole body: or of muche commi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion of the melancholy humor &amp; the bloude to gether / by the which the bloude is e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>fyred and chawfed: and ſo diſtendeth openeth and ſetteth abroade the vaynes whiche deſcende to the matrice. Alſo the bloude beynge very thynne and wateryſhe: for ſo it penetrateth / thrylleth / and yſſueth forthe the ſoner. Alſo yf the vaynes be very large / &amp; receaue much bloude: for in that caſe they ſende forthe the more agayn. Alſo yf the matrice be vnmygh<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ty &amp; weakened / the vaynes lykewyſe weake and large: ſo that they can not retayne nor witholde the bloude. Alſo yf the body of the woma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> or the outward partes be very denſe / clooſe / and compacte to gether: ſo that the outwarde powres be contracte and ſhut in ſuch wyſe that no vapours or ſwette can yſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſue out at them: then this ſhall cauſe the yll humoures (whiche otherwyſe wolde paſſe thorough the powres in ſwette) to remayne
<pb facs="tcp:16499:32" rendition="simple:additions"/>within the body / and there to engender and encreace greater fluxe and abou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter / which procedeth with the flowres &amp; au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gmenteth the quantite of them. Alſo yf the vaynes / whiche be named hemorroides / in the matrice be open and flowe forth. Alſo yf the matrice be peryſhed or otherwyſe viciat. Alſo yf it chanſe that the woman haue had a fall / or hath ben thruſt or beaten / by all and any of this meanes maye come this inordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nat fluxe of flowres.</p>
               <p>¶ Nowe ſtynge then that it enſueth by ſo manyfolde occaſions &amp; cauſes it ſhalbe mete that wome<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in this caſe be nothing aſhamed ne abaſhed to diſcloſe theyr mynde vnto ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pert phiſitians / ſhowyng them euery thyng in it / as they knowe where vppon it ſholde come: ſo that the phiſition vnderſtandynge the womans mynde / maye the ſoner by his learnynge and experience conſyder the true cauſe of it / and the very remedy to amend it. And many thinges there be which ſeaſe and reſtrayne this ouer much flowynge of flow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res: bothe electuaries / confections / trochiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes pouders / cliſteres / odoures / ſuffumigati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons bathes / plaſters and oyntementes / of
<pb n="xxxvi" facs="tcp:16499:32" rendition="simple:additions"/>whiche for the loue of women I wyll here ſet forthe the moſte principall and beſt.</p>
               <p>¶ Fyrſte then to ſtynte and reſtrayne the owtragius fluxe of flowres it ſhalbe verye good to bynde the armes very ſtrayght and ſtrongely &amp; not the fete or handes as: ſome vnwyſe men do teache / and then to ſet a ven<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>toſe or boxe or cup of glaſſe with fyre (which is called boxynge) vnder the breſtes / but cut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tynge no part of the ſkynne / layeng alſo lyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nen clothes dypped in vyn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e on the bellye betwene the nauell and the ſecreates: con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueyenge alſo into the places ſuche thynges / whiche haue vertue to reſtrayne bloude / as balauſtium / the ryne of pome granate / cara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>be / terra ſigillata / bole armenyacke / ſanguis draconis / hematites / the red roſe / whyte fran<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>kencenſe / and galles: all thoſe thynges or as manye of them as ye can conuenientlye get / beate them to powder in lyke portion / and temper them with thycke and groſſe wyne / making of it a plaſter / the whiche ſo te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pered put it in to a lyttell rounde bagge the quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tite of a mannes thombe the which ſhe ſhall put in to the preuye places.</p>
               <p>¶ Item an other plaſter to be miniſtred
<pb facs="tcp:16499:33" rendition="simple:additions"/>lykewyſe: Take of the bloudeſtone / called Emathites / bole armenyacke: of eche halfe an ounce: ſanguis draconis / licium / of ech .ij. dram<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s: Karabe: the cuppes of Acornes / Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe nuttes / Balauſtium or pſidiu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / of eche one dram<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: of the ſcales of yron one dram<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and an halfe: Turbyntyne and pyche lyke quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tite / or ſo muche as ſhalbe ſufficient to make a plaſter: beate and braye all theſe to gether / temperinge it to a plaſter: and then do with it as ye dyd with the other before.</p>
               <p>¶ An oyntemente for the ſame purpoſe: Take oyle Myrtine / oyle of rooſes / of eche halfe a pounde: Carabe / the ſcraping of yue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rye / the ſcrapynge of a gootes horne / redde corall: terra ſigillata / whyte frankencenſe / of eche one ounce / of white waxe .iij. ounces / all thoſe tempered to gether / make them in an oyntment / &amp; therewith annoynt the wombe and the ſecreates.</p>
               <p>¶ A batthe concernynge the ſame: Take wurmewud / plantayne the more &amp; the leſſe the toppes of vynes / freſſhe bra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ches of wyld mulberyes / vnrype damſenes ſlowes / or bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loes / wylde peres / medlers or myſpylles / of eche .iij. handefulles / of red rooſe leues thre
<pb n="xxxvii" facs="tcp:16499:33" rendition="simple:additions"/>handefulles / of oke barke .iiij. handfulles / of dayſes / of all ſortes of thyſtles / of eche .ij. handfulles: of cinkefoyle / the leues &amp; rotes / tormentyll the rootes / colubrine / of eche an handefull: alſo of acorne cuppes a ſaw ſer full / of gawlles / of acorns pylled / of burſa pa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtoris / of eche .ij. handefulles: beate all theſe to powder / cuttynge and broſynge that / that wyll not be beaten to powder / &amp; ſethe them to gether in rayne water / or els in water / in the which .x. or .xij. burnte ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ones haue bene quenchyd: this done / let the woman bathe herſelfe in this water vp to the nauell / and whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhe cometh forth of the bathe / geue her to drynke .ij. dram<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of electuarium athana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie / or miclete / wich plantayne water / or yf ſhe be ſore thurſtye with red wyne.</p>
               <p>¶ And lykewyſe ye maye geue vnto her of theſe electuaries that folow: take good olde rooſe ſugre .ij. ounces / of red corall / burnte yuery / bole armenyacke / of eche two dram<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s / of hematites thre dram<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s / beate all theſe thin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ges to gether / temperynge it with the rooſe ſugre / &amp; let her receaue of it in the mornynge and euenynge with two dram<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of plantane water / or els the water of burſa paſtoris.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:16499:34" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <p>¶ Item take the ſtone Emathites / &amp; rubbe it on a whetſtone / tyll the whetſtone ſeme redde / then waſhe it of agayne fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the whet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtone with plantaynewater / and ſo do often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tymes / vntyll ſuche tyme that thou haue a good quantite of it / and euery mornyng and euenynge let the woman drynke two or thre ſponefulles of the ſame.</p>
               <p>¶ Farthermore there be at the apotheca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries trochiſkes which helpe greately in this caſe / as the trochiſkes of karabe / and the tro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>chiſkes of bole armoniacke whiche muſte be miniſtred a dram<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> or more of ether of them / with .iiij. or .v. ſponeful of plantayne water. Who that requyreth farther in this matter let them aſke counſeill of the phiſytions / for we haue ſet here but ſuche thynges whiche may ſeme moſt neceſſarye.</p>
               <p>¶ Nowe yf it ſo be that there be engendred any apoſtume or other dyſeaſe in the preuye places after her labor / then moſte the apoſtu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mes and deſeaſes be clenſed / purged / &amp; hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led / the payne and ache of it mitigated and ſwaged with the iuyce of the beryes of ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latrum and the iuyce of plantane / alſo the oyle of rooſes / ſo that all theſe thynges be
<pb n="xxxviii" facs="tcp:16499:34" rendition="simple:additions"/>tempered to gether / and the places annoyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted therewith.</p>
               <p>¶ Ite<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> otherwyſe: take the wyte of an egge / woma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s mylke / the iuyce of purſelayne / and temper all theſe to gether / and conueye it to the dyſeaſed place / alſo let a bathe be made of water / in the whiche be ſoden pſida / redde roſe leues / the cuppes of acornes / oke barke / tormentyll / colubryne / and cinkefoyle / the le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues and the rotes / lette all theſe thynges be ſoden to gether / and in the water the woma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to bathe her ſelfe vp to the nauell: and after that the greued partes be healed and clenſed let the place be annoynted with vnguentum album / or vnguentum rubeum / whiche is to be had at the apothecaries / and with ſuche other thynges whoſe propertie be to refrige rate and coole. And loke what cure and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medies be mynyſtred to this places beyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge apoſtumate / or otherwyſe deſeaſed / the ſame alſo ſeruethe / yf the matrice or anye other parte of the ſecreates be rupte or bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken.</p>
               <p>¶ Manye tymes alſo it chanſeth that the foundament gut commeth forth both in ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and woman / and ſpetially in women in this
<pb facs="tcp:16499:35" rendition="simple:additions"/>buſyneſſe / by reaſon of theyr great labor and ſtryuynge with themſelfe: wherfore in this caſe it is the mydwifes parte with her hand warmed &amp; wet in whyt wyne / to reduce it backe into his place agayn / the which yf ſhe can not by this meanes / for becauſe that per aduenture it be ſwollen / then let her diſſolue butter in whyt wyne warmed / and there in dyp wooll with the which wrappe the ſame gutte a while / ſo doynge often tymes / tyll it be ſwaged / that it may be retorned in agayn and ye maye vſe in the ſtede of wyne luke warme mylke. And when it is thus retour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned and reduced into his place: take waxe / and melt it to gether with maſticke / or whyt frankencenſe / then ſprede it vpon lynne<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterwyſe / and laye it ouer the place where it came forthe byndynge it to it with a lynnen clothe or roller for partynge of / &amp; let this be done thus ſo ofte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as ſhe goythe to ſtole after that ſhe hath done / vntyll ſuche tyme that it be ſo ſetteled within / that it come no more oute / and yf ye wyll not occupye waxe / then dyp wooll in the oyle of maſticke or of ſpeke nardy / and lay it vnto the place ouer the fun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dament / byndynge it faſte vpon the place / as
<pb n="xxxix" facs="tcp:16499:35" rendition="simple:additions"/>before. ¶ Item another way: waſſhe &amp; ſoke the gut with the water in which is decoct &amp; ſoden ſuch thynges whiche exiccat drye and conſtrayne or combyne / as gaules / cypreſſe nuttes / ſpida / karabe / maſtick / frankencenſe / ſanguis draconis / and when it is well waſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed and ſoked with this water / then take the powder of an hartes horne burnte / and ſtrue it rounde aboute the gutte / and ſo re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtore it agayne in to his place.</p>
               <p>¶ Agayne yf it chanſe / that after the womans labor the matryce be remoued oute of his place / and appeare forthe / then lette it be waſſhed and ſoked with the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter in whiche be ſoden theſe thynges folow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ynge: take of cupreſſe nuttes / ſpicanarde / pſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>da / balauſtium / acorne cuppes / of eche an ounce: of meſpylles and vntype wylde pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res / &amp; vnrype aples / plummes / and dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſens or bolous: of eche a handefull and ſuch / of thoſe as be to be powdered beate them to powder and the reſte diuide / and cutte them ſmall: then ſeathe them all to gether in rayn water / or els in water in the whiche ſtele be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ynge red hote hathe ben often tymes quen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched: and in the ſame water lette the partie
<pb facs="tcp:16499:36" rendition="simple:additions"/>bathe her vp to the nauell / or els dyp a ſpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge or a locke of wooll in it / &amp; therewith waſſhe and ſoke the ſame matrice oftentymes then / euer with a fayre cleane lynnen clothe wype it cleane agayne &amp; ſtrewe vpon it the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der folowynge / beaten verye ſmall and ſear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched thorough ſylke.</p>
               <p>¶ Take of frankencenſe / karabe / galles / pſide / balauſtie / cypreſſe nuttes / alome / anty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monye / bole armoniacke / maſticke / of eche lyke much: beate theſe to very fyne powder / and ſtrewe the matrice with it / then tender<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye reduce it in to his place agayne with warme lynnen clothes byndynge it vp.</p>
               <p>¶ But yf ſo be that the matrice be ſwolle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / ſo that by this meanes it wyll not be reſtored to his naturall place agayne / then diſſolue butter in whyte wyne / as ye dyd before / and with the ſame ſoke it vnto ſuche tyme as it be aſſwaged / and then reduce it.</p>
               <p>¶ Agayne ſometyme it chanſeth that the womans nauell thoroughe labor is dyſſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued / ſo that it openeth it ſelfe: then make a ſmall tente of fyne lynnen / and anoynte it with this oyntement that foloweth / and the ſame put it in to the nauell: take whyte fran<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>kenſence
<pb n="xl" facs="tcp:16499:36" rendition="simple:additions"/>/ and beate it to powder / and then te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>per it with the whyte of an egge / ſo that it be after the manner of lyquyd honye: with this annoynte the nauell within and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oute / annoyntynge alſo the tente / the which beynge putte in the hole of the nauell bynde ſome clothe ouer it to kepe it in his place.</p>
               <p>¶ Item many tymes it chanſeth that tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowe the greate difficultie and thronges of labor the preuye parte and the foundament be come one / by reaſon of rupture and brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kynge of the ſame parte in the delyueraunce of the chylde / and that by that meanes the matrice deſcendeth and yſſueth downe / the whiche thynge chanſeth ſometymes by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon that the ſame place is very narowe and alſo tender / and the byrthe bygge / and of greate growethe / ſoo that it procedeth with ſuche violence / that it breakethe the waye before it.</p>
               <p>¶ When thys myſhappe fallethe / then fyrſte waſſhe and ſoke the matrice / and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoo reduce it to his place agayne / after the manner as I tolde you here immediatly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore / then heale theſe bracke &amp; wounde ſow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ynge of bothe ſydes of it to gyther agayne
<pb facs="tcp:16499:37" rendition="simple:additions"/>with a ſylken threde / as ſurgeons do other woundes: and yf that lyke ye not then / may ye cure it otherwyſe without ſowyng thus.</p>
               <p>¶ Take two lyttell peces of lynnen cloth / eche of the length of the wounde / &amp; in bredth two fyngers brode: ſpred the lyttell clothes with ſome faſte cleauynge plaſter the which wyll cauſe the clouthes to ſtycke faſt where they ſhalbe ſet / then faſten them the one on the one ſyde of the ryfte / the other on the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſyde / ſo that nothyng appeare betwene the peces of lynnen in the myddes of them / but onely the clefte and ryfte of the wounde in the breadthe of a ſtrawe / then this done / ſowe theſe ſydes of lynnen to gether cloſe as before I bed you to ſowe the ſkynne: &amp; when they be thus ſtytched to gether / laye a lyttell lyquyd pytche vpon the ſeme: and this done the lappes and ſydes of the wond vnder the lynnen plaſter wyll growe to gether agayne &amp; heale / &amp; the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> may ye remoue your plaſters.</p>
               <p>¶ I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> another way: take camfely dryed / &amp; beate it to powder / alſo cummyn and cyna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mome both beaten to powder / ioyne all thre to gether / and ſtrew of this powder into the wounde / and without faute it ſhall heale.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <pb n="xli" facs="tcp:16499:37" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <head>¶ Of aborcementes or vntymelye byrthes and the cauſes of it, and by what remedyes it maye be defended, holpen &amp; eaſed. ¶ Cap .viii.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Borcement or vntymely byrth is / when the woman is delyue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red before due ſeaſon &amp; before the frute be rype: as in the .iij.iiij. or .v. monethe before the byrth haue lyfe and ſometymes after it hath lyfe it is delyuered before it ſteare beynge by ſome chaunſe dead in the mothers wombe. Of the which thynge there be many and dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers cauſes.</p>
               <p>¶ Fyrſte ſometymes the mouth of the ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>trice is ſo large and ample / that it can not co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ueniently ſhytte it ſelfe to gether / nether con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne the feture or conceptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / or it is corrupt and infect with ſuch vicyous &amp; yll humours that it is ſo ſlyppery that the feture ſlyppeth and ſlydeth forth. Alſo ſometymes the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trice is apoſtumated &amp; ſore / ſo that for payne it can not contayne the conception.</p>
               <p>¶ Item ſometyme the cotilydons / that is the vaynes and ſynnues by the which the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ception and feature is tyed and faſtened in
<pb facs="tcp:16499:38" rendition="simple:additions"/>the matrice (through the which alſo the fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture receaueth noryſhment and fode) be ſtop<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ped with vyſcous and yll humours / or elles ſwollen by inflation / ſo that they breake / by the whiche meanes the feature deſtitute of his wont noryſhment peryſſheth and dyeth / and that moſte commonlye in the ſeconde or thyrde monethe after conception: wherfore Hypocrates ſayth: All ſuche women whiche be impregnat or conceaued being of a meane ſtate in her bodye / that is to ſaye / neyther to fat or groſſe / ne to ſpare or leane: yf it chanſe anye ſuche to aborce in the ſeconde or thyrde moneth (no other euident cauſe appearyng) knowe ye for certayne that it enſueth for be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the cotilydons be opplete / ſtopped / and ſtuffed with yll humours / &amp; be ſwollen and puffed therewith / that they breake / and ſo co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſeque<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly the feature dryeth for faute of fode.</p>
               <p>¶ Item aborcemente ſometyme commeth by reaſon that ſome of the places about the matrice be deſeaſed and greaued: as yf inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinum rectum / whiche is called the funda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment gutte be exulcerat / hauynge the pyles or hemorroides / or the vyſyke or bladder be ſwollen or encombred with the ſtone / the
<pb n="xlii" facs="tcp:16499:38" rendition="simple:additions"/>ſtrangurye / or other yll / in theſe caſes tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough the greate labor and payne the which the partie hathe in endeuourynge and enfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſynge her ſelfe other to ſtole or to make wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter / be engendred greate motions downe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde / by the whiche meanes manye tymes the cotylydons be enfringed and broken.</p>
               <p>¶ Alſo aborcement maye come of a diſeaſe called Tenaſmus / the whiche is when one hath euer greate deſyre and luſte to the ſtole and yet can do nothynge / neuer the leſſe the parties greately do enforce and payne them ſelfe to it / as Hypocrates ſayth: The preg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant woman which hath tenaſmum / for the moſte parte aborteth.</p>
               <p>¶ Item the coughe / yf it be greuous / cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth the ſame / and as the forenamed excelle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t phiſytiane ſayth / ſuch as are very ſpare and leane and brought lowe euermore lyghtlye dothe aborte / for becauſe that as Auicenna wryteth: all the meate and fode the whiche they receaue / turneth to the fode / noryſhme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t / and reſtauration of theyr owne bodyes / and ſo is the conception deſtitute of fode / wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore neceſſarily it dyeth.</p>
               <p>¶ Item this chanſe alſo commeth by ouer
<pb facs="tcp:16499:39" rendition="simple:additions"/>muche bleadynge or yſſuyng of the flowres / when they yſſue immoderatly. And ſo ſayth Hypocrates: Yf the woman yelde flowres af<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter her conception / it can not be that the fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture do longe proue / the which ſaying muſte be vnderſtande / yf they flowe vehementlye / or that the partie be weake and verye ſpare / or yf it be after the thyrde moneth / for it may be well that in the fyrſt and ſeconde moneth flowres maye yſſue / and yet no daunger / for as yet lyttell fode and noryſhment ſatiſfieth the conception.</p>
               <p>¶ Item to be let bloude / maye be the cauſe of aborcement as Hypocrates ſayth: whiche muſte be vnderſtande in ſuche as haue but lyttell ſtore of bloud: but ſuch as haue great copie &amp; plentie of bloude maye without any parell (yf any cauſe requyre it) be let bloude / ſo that it be after the .iiij. moneth and before the .vii. Howe be it I wolde that none ſhold be let bloude / except ſome greate and vrgent cauſe dyd requyre it.</p>
               <p>¶ Item it maye come by takynge of ſome ſtronge purgation before the .iiij. monethe &amp; after the vii. moneth / and yf it be ſo that any neceſſitie do ſo requyre that ſhe muſte nedes
<pb n="xliii" facs="tcp:16499:39" rendition="simple:additions"/>receaue a purgation / let it be done betwent the .iiij. and the .vij. moneth after the concep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: for then maye it be with leſt parell / and ſe that the purgation be very gentell &amp; eaſy.</p>
               <p>¶ Alſo this maye come by reaſon of a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuall fluxe / be it bloudy or otherwyſe / and ſpetially yf the woman be weake and ſpare / for by that meanes the conception is greate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly weakened and peryſhed. Item ouer much vomytynge may be cauſe of aborcement / for by ouer muche galpynge and reachynge vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes the cotilydons maye be broken / and ſo the feature to peryſſhe.</p>
               <p>¶ Item ouer muche famyne or hunger &amp; alſo ſharpe and faruent ſyckeneſſe maye be the cauſe hereof / as the peſtelence / apoſtume in the breſte / the ſoden palſie / the fallynge ſyckenes. &amp;c. Alſo ouer much dronkeneſſe &amp; exceſſe fedynge and ſurfetynge / by the which the byrthe is ſuffocat and ſtrangeled in the bellye and the fode corrupte for lacke of due digeſtion. Ite<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> yf the byrthe be ſycke by anye outwarde or inwarde cauſe / or yf the ſecon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyne in the which the feature is contayned / do breake before his tyme and the humours and waterres of the ſame flowe and yſſue
<pb facs="tcp:16499:40" rendition="simple:additions"/>forth / cauſeth the place to be ſlyppery / and ſo the byrth to ſlyde awaye vntymely / or yf the mother haue taken very greate colde / which maye ſone chanſe in the farre northe partes / or ouer greate heate / which weakeneth both mother and chylde. And therfore ought wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men with chylde to eſchue muche bathynge or goyng to the hote houſes in theyr temyng for that maye do hurte thre wayes / fyrſt that it kenleth &amp; enflameth the ayre or brethe con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tayned in the body / and ſo ſtyfleth the chylde and ſometymes the mother to / ſecondly that it relaxeth / diſſolueth / and loſeth the cotyly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s / and ſo maketh the byrth to yſſue forth / thyrdlye that the vtter hette of the bathe en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſeth the inwarde heate of the body / in ſo muche that the byrthe not beynge able to ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtayne and abyde the heate naturallye proce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth for refrigeration &amp; colynge / but in the tyme or about the tyme of labor ſhe may vſe bathes / as I declared before for the redyar and more expedite delyueraunce.</p>
               <p>¶ Item the intemperancie and mutation of the ayre / and whether maye be cauſe of aborcemente / for as Hypocrates wrytteth / 
<pb n="xliiii" facs="tcp:16499:40" rendition="simple:additions"/>when ſo euer the wynter is hote &amp; moyſt / &amp; the ſprynge tyde after colde and drye / ſuche women in that ſprynge tyde maye ſone and of a lyghte cauſe haue aborcement / or yf they aborce not / yet they ſhall be delyuered with greate payne / and the byrthe ſhall be verye weake and ſyckelye / ſoo that it ſhall dye ſtrayght / or yf it dye not by and by / it ſhall proue but verye ſlenderlye / the cauſe of the whiche thynge is this: for when that ſuche wynterynge chaunſeth / the hote and moyſte whether heateth and moiſteth the womans bodye / and by that the bodye is opened / vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>looſed / and reſolued / no leſſe then thought ſhe ware euery daye bathed / and vpon this when the ſprynge tyde cometh / yf it be colde and drye: fyndynge the body open and vnlo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed after ſuche ſorte / the colde entryth and percethe the bodye the ſoner and the more vehementlye / and the byrthe fealynge the ſoden colde and change of whether / pyneth awaye and dyethe in the mothers bellye / or anone after it is delyuered / or yf it lyue / it lykethe not / nor prouethe not / and greate payne ſhall it be to kepe lyfe in it.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:16499:41" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <p>¶ Item aborcement maye happen by ouer muche ſtearynge of the bodye in laborynge / daunſynge / or leapynge: or by ſome fall or thruſt agaynſt ſome wall / or beatynge / or by ſome ſodayne anger / feare / dredde / ſorowe / or ſome ſoden &amp; vnloked for ioye. Thus haue I reherſed all the cauſes of the whiche moſt commonlye maye enſue aborcemente or vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tymely byrth: the which no doubte is muche more grefe and vayne to the woma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> then the verye naturall labor / for ſuche thynges as chaunſe to man or woman contrarye to na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture / or before nature doth require it / is farre greater grefe then the ſame happenyng and commynge in his due ſeaſon.</p>
               <p>Sygnes wherby ye may forſee aborceme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t. When the woman ſhall labor before her tyme / theſe ſygnes are wonte to go before: Fyrſte her breſtes which before were hoole / ſounde / and full / ſhall begyn to were leſſe / to fall / and to flagge: &amp; then euer for the moſte parte aborcement foloweth. But yf it be ſo that ſhe go with two chyldre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> at once / yf one of the breſtes ſwage / whiche before was in good lykynge / the other remaynyng ſounde and ſafe / then loke of what ſyde the breſt is
<pb n="xlv" facs="tcp:16499:41" rendition="simple:additions"/>of / and the chylde of that ſyde is in parell / wherfore Hypocrates wryteth: Yf the ryght breſte ſlake or flagge / the maſculyne or male byrth is in parel: yf the left / the female byrth: for becauſe that for the moſt part whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> there be two at once / the one is maſculyne and the other femenyne / the man lyeth in the ryght ſyde / and the woman in the lefte.</p>
               <p>¶ Alſo an other ſygne of aborcemente is / when the woman hath greate paynes &amp; do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lours of the matrice / and that ſhe begyn to wexe redde in the face / and all partes of her bodye to ſhake and tremble / as thoughe it ware in a feuer / or the palſye in the heade. Item when ſhe feleth greate ache in the yn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner parte of the eyes towarde the braynes / the reſte of the bodye taken as it were with a weryneſſe and langueſſhynge / theſe thyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges portende and ſygnifye aborcement to be at hande / ſpetiallye yf at the ſame tyme the flowres yſſue alſo.</p>
               <p>¶ Item yf the womans body do ſwell and inflate with a certayne hardneſſe or ſtyfneſſe and that ſhe fele ſtytches and as it were ven toſyte or wynde runnynge frome one ſyde of the bodye to the other / and yet the belly not
<pb facs="tcp:16499:42" rendition="simple:additions"/>withſtandynge / beynge nothynge the more ponderous or wayghtye / and that the ſame inflacion do perſyſt and continue any whyle the woman takynge and eatynge ſuch thyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges which haue vertue to diſcuſſe and van<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſhe ventoſite &amp; wyndéneſſe: this thynge I ſaye dothe betoken parell of aborcemente throughe ventoſite and inflacion / and that chieflye aboute the thyrde or fourth moneth after the conception. Now haue I ſufficient<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly declared euident &amp; ſufficient ſignes where by maye be prouyded and forſene the aborce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment before it come / nowe wyll I ſhewe you the remedyes / whereby it maye be auerted and let.</p>
               <p>¶ The chiefe remedy to auoyde aborceme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t is: to auoyde &amp; ſhun all ſuch thynges which maye be cauſe of it / the whiche I haue com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petentlye entreated of alreadye: but yf ye feare aborcement becauſe that the mouth of the matrice be ouer ample and large / then muſte ye vſe ſuch thynges / whoſe operation is to contrahe / conſtrayne / and brynge to ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: as bathes / fumigations / oyntementes / plaſters / odours / and ſuche lyke / of the whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>the I ſpake before in the ſeuenthe chapter / 
<pb n="xlvi" facs="tcp:16499:42" rendition="simple:additions"/>and ſuche thynges the whyche repreſſe and ſtynte the flowres flowynge ouer muche af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the byrthe.</p>
               <p>¶ Agayne yf ye feare this parell / becauſe the mouthe of the matrice is moiſt and flyp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perye / other becauſe that the cotylydons be repleate and fulfylled with vyſcous hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours / and with inflations or ventoſytees: then maye ye defende it by vſynge of ſuche thynges / whoſe qualitees be to purifye / clen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe / exiccat / or drye / and to repreſſe ventoſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tees.</p>
               <p>¶ Howe be it / in all this matter lette not to make ſome experte phyſytyan of youre counſeill / yf ye maye haue ſuche one / for be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe that manye ſuche thynges come / and not all by one waye or meane.</p>
               <p>¶ And yf ye doubte parell / for becauſe that the matrice or other places aboute be infec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted / exulcerated / or appoſtumat / or hauynge the ſtone or ſtrangurye / and ſuch other thyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges / then aſke / and vſe the aduyſe of ſome well learned medycyne / and he ſhall ſhewe you howe all thynges ſhall be recured.</p>
               <p>¶ Yf agayne ye feare aborcement / becauſe the partye is very weake and lowe brought / 
<pb facs="tcp:16499:43" rendition="simple:additions"/>then let her feade on ſuch thinges the which moyſten and noryſſhe well or fatten the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dye / as capon fleſſhe / kydde / lamme / younge veale / partrige / and ſuche other.</p>
               <p>¶ Agayne yf the woma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> be taken with any ſharpe and fell deceaſe / then let her be cured of the ſame as ſhortelye as can be with ſuch thynges the whiche appertayne to the cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rynge of ſuche deſeaſe / or yf ſhe haue ſuſtay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned any longe famyne or hunger: then lette her be fedde with good meates and drynkes moderatlye taken / and yf ſhe haue ſurfeted by ouer muche eatynge and drynkynge (as nowe a dayes moſte commenlye people do) then let her abſteyne for a tyme / &amp; yf it maye be conuenientlye done / let her receaue ſome caſy &amp; gentyll medicine / which may alleuiat and lyghten her of her ſurfetynge burthen.</p>
               <p>¶ Now yf it ſo be / that the woma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> abounde in bloude / then ſhall it be very good a lyttell to let her bloude / bothe for her ſelfe and alſo for the byrthe / whiche throughe ouer muche adoundance of it myght happen to be ſuffo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated and ſtrangeled / of the which thynge al<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſo I haue ſpoken largely before.</p>
               <p>¶ Farthermore yf the woman feare abor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cement / 
<pb n="xlvii" facs="tcp:16499:43" rendition="simple:additions"/>by reaſon of contynuad coughe / or ouer muche vomyte and perbrakynge / or the fluxe / or of the deſeaſe called tenaſmus / or of ouer muche yſſuynge of bloude / whether it be by the noſe / or other partes of the bodye axe thaduyſe of a phyſitia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for remedy / yf for the fragilite / tendernes / and bracke / of the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condyne ſhe feare this aborcemente / for be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe that in this caſe the ſecondyne ſhall not be able to holde and contayne the byrth / as for this / there is no other medicine to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fende it / but onelye that the partie take hede that ſhe hurte not her ſelfe by ouer much mo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uynge or ſtearynge / as by laborynge / daun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſynge / runnynge / ſtandynge / faſte goynge / or caryenge of ponderous and weyghtye thyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges / or leftynge of the ſame. And to be ſhort / let her with all waryneſſe take hede and be diligent that ſhe exchue and abſtayne frome all ſuch thynges the which might cauſe and induce aborcement.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="chapter">
               <head>¶ Of deade byrthes, and by what ſygnes or to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kens it maye be knowen, and by what meanes it maye alſo be expelled. ¶ Cap .ix.</head>
               <pb facs="tcp:16499:44" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T ſhalbe nowe conuenient for vs to ſpeake of deade byrthes / howe it ſhall be knowen that they be deade / and howe they maye be expelled from the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. Sygnes then that the byrth is dead in the mothers wombe be theſe: j. Fyrſte yf the mothers breſtes do ſodenlye ſlake / as I touched before in the .viij. chapter .ij. Yf it moue it ſelfe no more beynge wont before to ſteare it ſelfe .in. Yf when the mother tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth her from the one ſyde on the other / ſhe feale it fallynge fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the one ſyde to the other lyke a ſtone or aded wayght .iiij. Yf her bellye and nauell begyn to were colde / whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che before was wont to be temperatly hote.</p>
               <p n="5">v. Yf anye ſtynkynge &amp; fylthye humours flowe from the matrice / &amp; chieflye after ſome fell deſeaſe .vi. Yf the womans eyes wexe holowe / &amp; that her color change from whyte to ſwarte and dunne coloure / and that her eyes and noſe wexe aſtoned / and haue not theyr ryght vſe / and her lyppes wexe wan.</p>
               <p n="7">vij. Yf benethe the nauell and aboute the ſecreate partes ſhe feale greate thronge and payne / the colour of her face changynge into
<pb n="xlviii" facs="tcp:16499:44" rendition="simple:additions"/>worſſe and worſſe / otherwyſe then it was wonte to do .viij. Yf ſhe haue appetyte to eate ſuche thynges / the whiche be agaynſte nature / and not wonte to be eaten or dron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken .ix. Yf ſhe be in her ſlepe vexed with bayne dreames .x. Yf ſhe be payned con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tynuallye with the ſtrangurye / or that ſhe enforce her ſelfe muche to the ſtole / and with all her power / and yet can not do any thing.</p>
               <p n="11">xi. Yf her brethe begynne to ſtynke / the whyche thynge lyghtlye happeneth two or thre dayes after the byrthe be deade.</p>
               <p n="12">xij. Yf her handes put in to verye warme water / and then layde on the womans bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye / and the chylde ſteare not / is a ſygne that it is deade.</p>
               <p>¶ Of all theſe ſygnes nowe the more that come to gether of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> at one tyme &amp; in one ꝑ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon / the ſurer may ye be that the byrth is ded the which being ones ded / all diligence muſt be had that it may be expelled out of the wo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mans body: but here muſt ye ſe agayne whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it maye be expelled / the mothers lyfe ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued or no / for ſome tyme it chaunſeth that the mother dyeth with all / and ſometymes the mother dothe well and proſpereth.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:16499:45" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <p>¶ Whether the mother ſhall be in parell withall or no / by theſe thinges ſhal ye know yf the woman beynge in the labor ſowne or fare as thoughe ſhe ware in a tranſe / yf her remembraunce fayle her / and ſhe waxe fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and ſcant able to mou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e or ſteare herſelfe / yf ſhe (called with a lowde voyce) canne an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere nothynge at all / or els very lyttell and that verye ſoftelye / as thoughe her voyce be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to fayle her: yf ſhe be inuaded or taken among in the laborynge with conuulſion or ſhrynkeling to gether: if ſhe refuſe or can not broke meate / yf her pulces beate verye faſte / the which ſygnes when ye ſe in the woman laborynge: it is an ruident toke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that ſhe ſhal not liue long after her byrth / wherfore co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mit the cure of her to the handes of almyghtye god / but yf none of theſe ſygnes do appeare / then haue good hope / for the woman ſhall do well / the byrthe beynge once departed: wherfore geue all diligence to the expultion of it / that the woman maye be delyuered of this dead burthen: the whiche thinge maye be done by two wayes / other by medicines expulſyue / or elles by certayne inſtrumentes made for the nonce.</p>
               <pb n="xlix" facs="tcp:16499:45" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <p>¶ Fyrſte without inſtrumentes with this fumigation: take other the houe or dunge of an aſſe / and put it on coles / and lette the woman receaue the fume vndernethe. Ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: take the ſkynne of an adder / myrrhe / ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoreum / brymſtone / galbanum / oppopona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cum / madder that the dyerres occupye / pyge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons dunge / or hawkes dunge: beate all theſe to powder / and temper them with oxe gall / and make pylles of it eche of the quantite of a fylbert nutte / and then put one after ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in the coles / and receaue the fume tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowe a pype or conduyte made for that pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe in to the priuities.</p>
               <p>¶ Another: take encenſe / oppoponacum / galbanum / brymſtone / of eche lyke muche / beate them to gether and temper them with oxe galle / and make pylles of them / and then of the ſame make fumigations / as before.</p>
               <p>¶ A potion for the ſame purpoſe: take aſa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fetida halfe a dram<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / of rue iij. dram<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s / of myr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rhe .ij. dram<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s: &amp; beate them to powder / and geue to the woman at eche tyme a dram<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of this powder with whyte wyne / or with wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter in the which ſauyne is ſoden.</p>
               <p>¶ Another: take fygges / fenegreke / organ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nye / 
<pb facs="tcp:16499:46"/>and ſethe them in water the which gene vnto the woman to drynke / for this drynke wyl engendre lubrycyte and ſlypperyneſſe in the nether partes / and vſe alſo ſome of thoſe thynges whiche haue vertue to prouoke the byrth / wherof we entreated before.</p>
               <p>¶ Item certayn peſſaries or ſuppoſitaries concernynge the ſame: take gumme armo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niacke / oppoponacum / helleborus niger / ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phiſagre / ariſtolochia longa / &amp; colocynthis without his kernelles: beate all theſe thyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges to gether / temperyng them with oxe gall and alſo with the iuyce of freſſhe rue / then make a peſſarie of wollen / and annoynt and wet the peſſarie with the ſame / conueynge it into the ſecreate places.</p>
               <p>¶ Item another: make a peſſarie of wolle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the lengthe &amp; thyckeneſſe of a fynger / and do it in the iuyce of rue in the which is diſſol<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ued a quantitie of ſcammome / and do with that peſſarie / as before.</p>
               <p>¶ Item take ariſtolochia rotunda / ſauyne / garde creſſes / of eche lyke muche / beate them to powder / and temper them with oxe gall: with this annoynt a peſſarie made and orde<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>red as before is ſpoken of. Item yf the wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man
<pb n="l" facs="tcp:16499:46"/>drynke the mylke of another woman / it wyll ſteare and expell the byrth.</p>
               <p>¶ Item take of the iuyce of dyttayne or of the powder of the roote of the ſame herbe .ij. dram<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s / and geue the ſame to drynke to the woman with wyne / excepte ſhe be in greate heate / for then ſhall ye geue it her with luke warme water / and this ſhall expell the dead byrth without any parell of the mother.</p>
               <p>¶ Item take of myrrhe .iiij. drammes / of cinamome / galbanum / caſtoriu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / of eche two drammes: of oppoponacum one dram<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: all thoſe beaten / and tempered to gether with oxe gall / make pylles of them / wayenge eche of them a dram<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / and with the fume of thoſe perfume the nether partes / by this vapoure the deade byrthe is broughte forthe / infla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation and ſuffocation of bloude is expel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led.</p>
               <p>¶ Item take of water mynte / ſothern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wood / muggewort / of eche a handefull / of aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phaltum halfe an ounce / of madder two oun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ces and an halfe / of camomell / barotum / fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>negreke / of eche two ounces: ſethe all theſe thynges to gether in rayne water: in the whyche lette the woman bathe her ſelfe / 
<pb facs="tcp:16499:47" rendition="simple:additions"/>then take of henſgrece and duckes grece / of eche .iiij. dram<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s: to the which adde two oun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of oyle of anues ſede / with this oyntme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t annoynt the woma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s head comminge out of the bath: then take dateſtones &amp; beate them to powder a dram<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and a halfe / with a ſcru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of ſafrane tempered to gether with whyt wyne: the which let her immediatlye drynke after ſhe come forthe of the bathe.</p>
               <p>¶ Item take oppoponacum / &amp; make there of a peſſarye the quantitie of a fynger / con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueye it into the priuities / this expelieth the dead byrth.</p>
               <p>¶ Item take of galbanum a dram<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> or ſome what leſſe: of gotes mylke an ounce and a halfe or two ounces in the which the galba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num beynge diſſolued / geue it to the woman to drynke.</p>
               <p>¶ Item a plaſter for the ſame: take galba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num beaten and tempered with the iuyce of motherworte / and of this make a plaſter by puttyng to of wexe a certayne qua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tite / than take a lynnen cloth of ſuche length &amp; bredth that it maye couer all the belly vnder the na<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uel to the priuities fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> one ſyde to the other / on this cloth ſpred this plaſter of the thycke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe
<pb n="li" facs="tcp:16499:47" rendition="simple:additions"/>of a ſtrawe / and laye it to the bellye. Item take the tryacle which is called diateſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaron: and geue of it to the woman for to drynke / and it wyll expell this dead byrth.</p>
               <p>¶ But yf all theſe medicines profette not / then muſte be vſed more ſeuere and harde re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>medyes / with inſtrumentes / as hokes / ton<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges / and ſuche other thynges made for the nonce. And fyrſt the woman muſt be layde a longe vpryght / the myddell parte of her bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dye lyeng hyer then all the reſte / companyed of women aſſiſtynge her aboute to comforte her / and to keape her downe / that when the byrthe is plucked oute ſhe ryſe not withall. Then let the mydwyfe annoynt her left ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d with the oyle of whyte lyllyes or other that may make it ſople and ſmouth: and holding out her fyngers ſhytting to gether her hand let her put it to the matrice to feale and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaue after what faſſhion the dead byrth ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth in the mothers wombe: ſo that ſhe maye the better putte in hokes and ſuche other in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrumentes to plucke it out with all.</p>
               <p>¶ Yf it be ſo that it lye the head forewarde / then faſten a hoke other vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> one of the eyes of it / or the rofe of the mouthe / or vnder the
<pb facs="tcp:16499:48" rendition="simple:additions"/>chyn / on one of the ſholders / whiche of theſe partes ſhall ſeme moſte commodious and handſome to take it oute bye / and the hoke faſtened to drawe it oute verye tenderlye for hurtynge of the woman.</p>
               <p>¶ But yf it lye the fete forewarde / then fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſten the hoke on the bone aboue the priuye partes / or by ſome ribbe / or ſome of the backe bones / or of the breſte bones / and when this hoke is thus faſtened / the midwyfe may not by and by drawe and plucke at it / but hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dynge it in her lefte hande / lette her with her ryghte hande faſten another in ſome other parte of the byrthe ryght agaynſte the fyrſte / and then tenderlye let her drawe both to ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther / ſo that the byrth may procede and come forthe on bothe ſydes equallye / mouynge it from one ſyde to another / tyll ye haue gotte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> out alto gether / and nowe and then to helpe it in the comming forth with the fore fynger well annoynted / if it chanſe to ſtycke or to be let any where: and as it commeth forthe / al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waye to remoue the hokes farther and far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther on the dead byrthe.</p>
               <p>¶ Agayne yf it chanſe that one of the han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des onely of the byrth do appeare / &amp; that it
<pb n="lii" facs="tcp:16499:48" rendition="simple:additions"/>can not conuenientlye be reduced &amp; returned vpwarde agayne / by reaſon of the narow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the place / then byndt it with a lynne<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> cloth / that it ſlyp not vp agayne / and then to plucke it outwarde / vntyll ſuche tyme that the hole arme be out and then with a ſharpe knyfe cut it of from the body / and euen ſo do yf both handes appeare fyrſte at once / or one legge or bothe / yf they can not be returned backe / to be otherwyſe taken out conuenient lye / as ye cutte the arme frome the ſholders / ſoo lykewyſe cuttinge the legges frome the thyghes / for the which purpoſe the ſurgeo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s haue me<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e inſtrumentes made for the nonce with the which ſuch legges and armes may ſone be cut frome the bodye / theſe partes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ynge once reſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>te and cutte frome the bodye / then turne the teſte / ſo that it maye eaſylye procede with as lyttell payne to the mother / as maye be.</p>
               <p>¶ Yf it be ſo that the chyldes head be ſoo ſwollen by inflation / ſwellynge / or reſorte of humours that it wyl not conueniently yſſue oute that narowe places / then let the myd<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wyfe with a ſharpe penknyfe cutte open the heade / that the humours contayned in it
<pb facs="tcp:16499:49" rendition="simple:additions"/>maye yſſue and runne forth / and ſo the head to waxe leſſe able to be plucked out: but yf it ſo be that not by any ſuche caſualte the head be bygge / but onely of a naturall groweth / then muſte the head be broken in peces / and the partes euermore taken forth with ſuche inſtrumentes / as the ſurgeons haue readye and neceſſarye for ſuche purpoſes.</p>
               <p>¶ Agayn yf that after the head were come forthe / yet the breſte parte wolde not folowe for greateneſſe / then muſte ye breake and cut lykewyſe that parte / vnto ſuche tyme that it maye be had forth. And euen ſo lykewyſe / yf all the reſt of the bodye ſholde be ſo ſwol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len that it wolde not procede ne come forth / then muſte it lykewyſe be broken in peces / &amp; ſo had forthe.</p>
               <p>¶ Farthermore if by chanſe or byſeaſe it co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me to paſſe that the mouth of the matrice be exulcerat or apoſtumat / ſo that the paſſage be made the narower by that meanes / the dryer and the more contracte / then muſte ye fyrſte ſtudye and endeuour you to ſople and eaſe the places by oyles &amp; other greces / ſuche as I ſpake of ſufficientlye before in the fyfth chapter with bathes and fumigations.</p>
               <pb n="liii" facs="tcp:16499:49" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <p>¶ Alſo yf the dead byrth come ſydelonge / then muſte ye do what maye be doue to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerte &amp; torne it to ſuch faſhion / that it maye moſte eaſyly be brought forth: the matrice &amp; other ſecreates muſte be annoynted / perfu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med / and vapored with ſuche thinges / the which maye make it more ample &amp; large / yf it can not be thus had forthe hole: then let it be cut out by peſe mele / as is before ſpoken of. And yf after this delyueraunce the flow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res yſſue ouer vehementlye / then vſe ſuche thynges as haue vertue to reſtrayne them / of the which I haue ſpoken in the .vij. chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter before. But co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trary to all this / yf it cha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſe that the woman in her labor dye / &amp; the chyld hauyng lyfe in it / the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhall it be mete to kepe open the woma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s mouth / and alſo the nether places / ſo that the chylde maye by that mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes bothe receaue &amp; alſo expell ayre &amp; brethe which otherwyſe myght be ſtopped / and the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to turne her on the left ſyde / &amp; there to cutte her open / &amp; ſo to take out the chylde / &amp; they that are borne after this faſhion be called ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſares / for becauſe they be cut out of theyr mo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thers belly / whervpon alſo the noble Roma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ne ceſar the .j. of that name i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Rome toke his name.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="chapter">
               <pb facs="tcp:16499:50"/>
               <head>¶ Howe the infante newlye borne, muſte be handled, nouryſhed, and loked to. ¶ Cap .x.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Fter that the infant is once borne / by &amp; by the nauel muſt be cutte thre fyngers bredthe from the belly / &amp; ſo knyt vp: then as Auice<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>na wryteth / let be ſtrued on the head of that that remayneth / of the powder of bole arme nyacke / &amp; ſanguis draconis / ſarcocolla / myr<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rha and comyne / of eche lyke much beaten to powder / ſtrewe on the cut of that pece that remayneth / then vppon that bynde a pece of wooll dypped in oyle olyfe that the powder fall not of: ſome vſe fyrſt to knyt the nauell / and after to cutte it ſo much / as is before re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herſed.</p>
               <p>¶ And farthermore ſome ſay that of what length the reſte of the nauell is lefte / of the ſame length ſhall the chyldes tonge be / yf it be a man chylde. Item Auicenna ſayth that dyuers thynges maye be knowen by mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kynge of the chyldes nauell / for as he ſayth / when the woman is delyuered of her fyrſte chylde / then beholde the nauell of the childe / 
<pb n="liii" facs="tcp:16499:50" rendition="simple:additions"/>which yf in that parte of it which is next vn to the body it haue neuer a wryncle / it proten deth and doth ſignifye perpetuall fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thenſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forth ſterilite or barenneſſe / &amp; yf it haue any wrynkles in it / then ſo manye wrynkles / ſo many chyldren ſhal the woma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> haue in tyme to come. Alſo ſome adde to this &amp; ſaye: that yf there be lytteli ſpace betwene theſe wryn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kles in the nauell / then ſhall there be alſo lyttell ſpace betwene the barynge of the chyl<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dren / yf muche / it ſyngnifyeth longe tyme be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twene the barynge of them.</p>
               <p>¶ Nowe to returne to our purpoſe / when that the nauel is cut of / &amp; the reſte knytte vp: annoynt all the chyldes bodye with the oyle of acornes / for that is ſyngularly good to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme / ſtedfaſt / and to defende the body from noyſom thinges / whiche may chaunſe from without: as ſmoke / colde / &amp; ſuche other thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges which yf the infant be greaued with all / ſtreate after the byrth / being yet very tender / it ſholde hurte it greately.</p>
               <p>¶ After this annoyntynge waſſhe the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fant with warme water / and with your fyn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ger (the nayle beynge pared) open the chyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des noſeſtrelles / and purge them of the fyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thyneſſe.
<pb facs="tcp:16499:51" rendition="simple:additions"/>Item it ſhalbe good to put a lyttell oyle into the eyes: and alſo that the mother or nource handle ſo the childes ſyttyng place that it maye be prouoked to purge the belly. And chieflye it muſte be defended from ouer much colde or ouer muche heate.</p>
               <p>¶ After that that the parte extante or bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging forth of the nauell is fallen / the whiche commonlye chanſeth after the thyrde or .iiij. daye then on the reſte remaynyng ſtrewe the powder or aſſhes of a calfes houe burnt / or of ſnayle ſhelles / or the powder of ledde / cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led redde ledde / tempered with wyne.</p>
               <p>¶ Farthermore when the infant is ſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deled and layde in cradell / the nource muſte geue all diligence and hede that ſhe bynde euerye parte ryght and in his due place and order / and that with all tenderneſſe and gen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tell entreatynge / and not crokedlye and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſely / the which alſo muſte be done oftenty<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mes in the daye: for in this is it as it is in younge and tender ympes / plantes / &amp; twyg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges / the whiche euen as ye bowe them in theyr youthe / ſo wyll they euermore remayn vnto aege. And euen ſo the infante yf it be bounde and ſwadeled / the membres lyenge ryght &amp; ſtrayght / then ſhall it growe ſtreate and vpryght / yf it be crokedlye handled / il wyll growe lykewyſe / and to the yll negli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence
<pb n="lv" facs="tcp:16499:51" rendition="simple:additions"/>of many nources may be imputed the crokedneſſe and deformite of manye a man and woman / which otherwyſe myght ſeme well fauered as any other.</p>
               <p>¶ Item let the chyldes eyes be oftentymes wyped and clenſed with a fyne and cleane lynnen clothe or with ſylke: and let the ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes of the infante be verye ſtrayght layde downe by the ſydes / that they maye growe ryght / and ſometyme ſtrokynge the bellye of the chyld before the veſike of bladder to help to eaſe and to prouoke the chylde to the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kynge of water / and when ye laye it in the cradell to ſlepe / ſet the cradell in ſuch a place that nether the beames of the ſonne by daye nether of the mone by nyght come on the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fant: but rather ſet it in a darke and ſhadow place: layenge alſo the head euer ſomewhat hyer then the reſte of the bodye.</p>
               <p>¶ And farther lette it be waſſhed two or thre tymes in the daye / and that anone after ſtepe in the wynter with hote water / in the ſommer with luke warme water: nether let it tary long in the water but vnto ſuch tyme as the body begyn to waxered for hete: but take hede that none of the water come in to the infantes eare / for that ſhulde greatelye hurte his hearynge another daye.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:16499:52" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <p>Then to be ſhorte / when it is taken oute of the bathe / let it be wyped and handeled with gentell and ſofte lynnen cloth warmed / and then to laye it on her lap the backe vpward / the whiche with her handes let her tenderly ſtroke and rubbe / and then to lappe it vppe / and to ſwadell it / &amp; when it is ſwadeled / to put a drop or two of water in to the noſtrel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les of it / is very good for the eye ſyght. And ſo laye it to reſte.</p>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>¶ Of the nourſe, and her mylke, and howe longe the chylde ſholde ſoucke.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S conternynge the bryngynge vp nouriſſhement and geuyng of ſucke to the chylde / it ſhall be beſt / yf the mother geue her chyld ſucke herſelfe / for the mo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thers mylke is more conuenient and agrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to the infante then anye other womans / and more dothe it nouryſſhe it / for becauſe that in the mothers bellye it was wonte to the ſame and fedde with it / and therfore alſo it dothe more deſyrouſlye couet the ſame / as that / with the which it is beſt acque<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted / and to be ſhorte / the mothers mylke is moſt hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomſte
<pb n="lvi" facs="tcp:16499:52" rendition="simple:additions"/>for the chylde. As Auicenna writeth: it ſhall be ſufficient to geue it ſucke twyſe or thryſe in a daye. And alwayes beware / ye geue not the chylde to much ſucke at once in this tender aege of it / for clowyng of it / and leſte alſo it lothe it / but rather let it haue of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten of it / and lytell at once / then fewe tymes / and ouer muche at once. For ſuch as be ouer clowed with the mothers mylke / cauſethe theyr body to ſwell and inflate / and in theyr vrine ſhal it appeare that it is not ouer come ne concocied or digeſted in the chylde / which thyng yet yf it chaunſe / let the infant be kept faſtinge / vntyll ſuch tyme as that the which it hath receaued already / be compleately di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſted. Item yf the mothers mylke be ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what ſharpe or egre / lette her neuer geue the chylde her breſte faſtynge.</p>
                  <p>¶ Yf it be ſo that the mother can not geue the infant ſucke herſelfe / ether for becauſe of ſyckeneſſe or that her breſtes be ſore and her mylke corrupted: then let her choſe a holſom nurſe with theſe conditions folowynge.</p>
                  <p>¶ Fyrſte that ſhe be of a good coloure and complexion / and that her bulke and breſte be of good largeneſſe. Secondly that it be not
<pb facs="tcp:16499:53" rendition="simple:additions"/>to ſone after her labor / ne to longe after / ſo that it be two monethes after her labor at the leſte / and that (yf it maye be) ſuche one whiche had a man chylde / thyrdelye that ſhe be of meane and meaſurable lykynge / ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to fatte ne to leane. Fourthelye that ſhe be good and honeſt of conuerſation / neyther ouer haſtye or yrefull ne to ſad or ſoleme / ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to fearefull or timorous: for theſe affec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and qualitees be parnicious and hurt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to the mylke / corruptynge it / and paſſe forth through the mylke in to the chylde / ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>kynge the chylde of lyke condition and man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners / alſo that they be not ouer lyght &amp; wan<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ton of behauoure. Fyftelye that her breſtes be full and haue ſufficient plentie of mylke: and that they be neyther to great / ſofte / han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gynge / and flaggynge / ne to lyttell / harde / or contracte / but of a meaſurable quantitie.</p>
                  <p>¶ Alſo loke vpon her mylke / that it be not blackyſſhe / blueyſſhe / grey or reddyſſhe / ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſowre / ſharpe / ſaltyſſhe / or brackyſſhe / nether thyn &amp; fluye / neyther ouer groſſe and thycke: but temperatly whyte and pleaſante in taſte: and to be ſhorte: that mylke is beſte and moſte to be choſen of the whiche a drop
<pb n="lvii" facs="tcp:16499:53" rendition="simple:additions"/>beynge mylked ſoftelye on the nayle of the thombe holdyng your fynger ſtyll / it rolleth not of / nether flytteth abrode / but yf ye moue your hand a lyttell it will ſlyde of by and by: but yf whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it is mylked on the nayle it ſpred abrode / &amp; flyt by &amp; by / then is it to thyn: but yf it cleaue ſtyll when that ye moue a lyttell youre hande then is it ſo ſpyſſe &amp; thycke / the meane betwene bothe is beſte.</p>
                  <p>¶ Yf it be ſo / that the nourſes mylke be to hote or ſharpe / then lette her neuer geue the chylde ſucke her ſelfe beynge faſtynge.</p>
                  <p>Sometyme it chaunſeth / that the mothers or nourſes mylke dothe fayle or decreaſe / the which thynge maye come by dyuers cauſes: as by ſyckeneſſe / by deceaſe in the breſtes / or by takyng of colde in the ſame / and ſo ſtoppe and cludder the mylke: or for becauſe ſhe lac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kethe ſuche thynges / the whiche myght en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gender mylke / other by ouer muche faſtinge / hungre / and thurſte: the whiche cauſes muſt be well conſydered / and then accordynge to that minyſter a remedy.</p>
                  <p>¶ Thinges which do augment &amp; encreaſe mylke / be thoſe: let her vſe to eate parſenyp / other the ſede or the rote. Alſo the ſede or
<pb facs="tcp:16499:54" rendition="simple:additions"/>rote of fenell ſoden in the brothe made with barley or cicercula: let her eate of that with other meates that ſhe feadeth on. Item to eate ſhepes breſte and the mylke of them is good. Item take an ounce of cowe butter / &amp; diſſolue it in warmed wyne / the which lette the nource drynke. Item boxynge vnder the breſtes doth well / not cuttynge the ſkynne.</p>
                  <p>¶ Item a plaſter for the ſame of franken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence / maſtycke / and pytche layde to the bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes or vnder the breſtes the ſkynne fyrſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yng annoynted with oyle / left it ſhold cleaue ouer faſte to the place. Item it ſhalbe verye good to rubbe ſoftelye with the hande the breſtes / or elles in bathynge after dynner or ſupper to cauſe ſome to ſucke her breſte.</p>
                  <p>Item take the oyle of white lyllyes or of vio<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lettes / and myngle with it muſke / encenſe / &amp; laudanum well tempered to gether / in the ſame dyppe a peſe of wooll / and clappe it to the breſtes / and ſoke them with it. Item waſſhe them / and ſoke them often tymes with wyne / in the which is decoct and ſoden myntes / roſes / violettes / and xiloaloes. Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo to eate of the brothe in the which is ſoden a henne / with cynamome / maces / and carda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>momum
<pb n="lviii" facs="tcp:16499:54" rendition="simple:additions"/>/ and alſo the yowlke of an egge. Item it is good for her to eate freſſhe cheſe and mylke / and to refrayne frome all maner of greate labor and harde workes. Alſo po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage made of beane meale / ryſe / and breade made of fyne flowre / tempered with mylke and ſugre / putting to it alſo a quantite of fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nell ſede or of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eues / is very good for her.</p>
                  <p>¶ Item take of anys ſede / of ſyler monta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num / of eche .iii. dram<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s / of chriſtall beten to powder. u. dram<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s / &amp; as muche of ſugre / geue her this to drynke aboute .x. dayes at mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning / euening / &amp; myddaye. Ite<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> take of fenell ſede or the leues / &amp; of horehownde of eche .ij. ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ofulles / of ams ſede iiij. dram<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s / of ſafrane beaten one ſcruple: alſo of freſſhe butter .iij. ounces / &amp; ſethe all theſe in ſufficient water / makynge hereof a plaſter / &amp; the ſame plaſter whylſt it is hote / laye it to the nourſes breſt.</p>
                  <p>¶ Item take of comyn ſede an ounce &amp; an halfe / &amp; of clarifyed hony .iij. ounces: ſethe it in .vi. li. wayght of water alto gether beynge put into a newe pot &amp; let it ſethe to the thyrd parte / &amp; of this decoction geue the nourſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ofte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tymes to drynke. Ite<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> take of beetes well waſſhed one ounce: of co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>myn halfe an ounce
<pb facs="tcp:16499:55"/>of hony .vi. ounces: of theſe myngled &amp; tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pered to gether / make an electuarie / of the which let her take both in the morninge and eueninge at eche tyme a ſponefull. Ite<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> take two dram<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of cryſtal beate<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> into fyne pouder &amp; deuyde that in foure equall partes / one of theſe partes geue vnto the nourſe the ſpace of .iiij. dayes to drynke / with brothe made other of cicer / or els of peaſon: alſo all thoſe thinges folowing encreaſe &amp; augme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t mylke in the breſtes: annes &amp; annes ſede / dyll &amp; the ſede / horehownde / cardomome / freſſhe cheſe / wortes made of olde ehece / cicer / criſlal beate<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to powder &amp; take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with hony: lettuſe / fenell / wyne in which roſemary or ſerpillu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> be ſode<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Ite<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to abſtayne fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> venery or mans co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pany / for yf ſhe vſe that / it ſhall ſpende &amp; conſume the mylke &amp; make it vnſauery &amp; vnholſome: nether can the chylde well broke it / but moſt co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>menly ſhall caſt it vp again / becauſe it can not digeſt it Alſo it ſhalbe beſt that the child ſucke not of the mothers breſte by and by as ſone as it is borne: but rather of ſome other womans for a daye or two / for becauſe that the creme (as they cal it) ſtreit after the byrth the fyrſt daye in all women doth thycke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and
<pb n="lix" facs="tcp:16499:55"/>congeyle. ¶ Item yf it chaunſe that the nourſe be ouer ſore laxed / or that ſhe be ouer bounde / ſo that ſhe take anye medycynes to remedye it / then let another geue the chylde ſucke / whylſt ſhe be recouered agayne. And when the chylde is layde in cradell to be roc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked: rocke not to faſt / leſt through ouer much rockyng and ſtearyng the chyldes ſtomacke torne and the mylke there corrupte for lacke of reſt. ¶ Auicen auyſeth to geue the chyld ſucke two yeres / howe be it amonge vs moſt commenlye they ſucke but one yeare. And when ye wyll wene them / then not to do it ſodenly / but a lyttell and lyttell / and to make for it lyttell pylles of breade &amp; ſugre to eate &amp; accuſtome it ſo / tyll it be able to eate all ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of meate: &amp; this ſhall ſuffyce for the edu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation and bryngynge vp of infantes at this tyme / notwithſtandinge dyuers other thyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges here are lefte vnſpoken of / another tyme god willyng we ſhall declare them at large.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <trailer>¶ Thus endeth the fyrſte boke.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="book">
            <pb facs="tcp:16499:56" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>THE SECONDE BOKE.</head>
            <div type="illness">
               <head>¶ Of dyuers deceaſes and infirmities whiche chaunſe to chyldren lately borne, and the remedyes therefore.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>L thoughe there be in manner infinite deceaſes which happe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to infantes / as wryteth Hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crates / Galenus / Raſis / Amce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na / and diuers other: yet for bre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uite and ſhortneſſe we wyll reherſe here on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſuch of them / which moſte commenly hap<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pen to the ſame / and that be thoſe: Exulcera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the gummes / flyx of the belly or ouer much looſeneſſe of the ſame / the belly hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bownd / the crampe / the cough / &amp; diſtillation of the heade / ſhort wynded / bladders on the tounge / exulceration or chyppynge of the mouthe / apoſtume in the eares / apoſtume in the brayne / ſwellynge and bolnynge of the eyes / ſkum or creme of the eyes / the feuer / knawynge in the bellye / the body ſwellynge and puffed vp / often ſneeſynge / whelkes or bladders on the bodye / ſwellynge of the cod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des / ſwelling of the nauell / vnſlepyneſſe / yex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ynge / appetyte to perbrake / fearefulnes in the dreames / the mother / yſſuyng out of the fondament gut / wormes in the belly / chaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fynge / 
<pb n="lx" facs="tcp:16499:56" rendition="simple:additions"/>the fallynge ſyckeneſſe / the conſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyon / the palſye / trymblynge of the partes of the bodye / the ſtone / gogell eyes.</p>
               <p>¶ Howe to cure and to remedye all theſe / nowe wyll I ſhewe in order. Fyrſt in exulce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of the gummes are wonte certayne puſſhes and as it were wheles grow on the gummes or in the corners of the iawes / the which put the place to muche greuance: and to remedie this it ſhall be good that ye with your fynger rubbe the infa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes gummes and the puſſhes or whelkes with all: and then to annoynt the ſame gummes with oyntment made of hennes greſe / hares brayne / oyle of camomell mixt with honye / other els turpen tyne tempered with hony / then take water / and in it ſethe camomell and dyll / the which water beynge hote: powre it on the chyldes heade / holdynge it a fote aboue the heade.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="illness">
               <head>¶ Of the flyx or ouer muche looſeneſſe of the bellye.</head>
               <p>For this take the ſede of roſes / cu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>myn / anyſe and the ſede of ſmalege: beate all thoſe toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and make them plaſter wyſe / and laye it to the chyldes bellye: yf it ſtynte not by this
<pb facs="tcp:16499:57" rendition="simple:additions"/>remedye / then take of the coagulu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of a kyd a halfe peny wayght or a lyttell more / &amp; geue it to the chylde to drynke with colde water / and all the ſame daye let the chylde be kepte frome ſuckynge / leſte the mylke ſhulde curde in the ſtomacke of it / but in the meane whyle let it eate of the yowlke of poched egges / or of whyte breade ſoden in water.</p>
               <p>¶ And farther yf that it whiche the infant voydeth be of / redde or yelowe colour / then lette drynke, of the ſyrupe of roſes / or of crab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bes / other elles of pome granates / tempered with a lyttell mynte water.</p>
               <p>¶ Item another medycyne: take leuen and in water breake it / &amp; let it ſtype a whyle / then ſtrayne it throughe a lynnen cloth / then take of the ſyrupe of violettes the wayghte of an halfe peny / of ſpodium / called burnt yuerye / the wayght of a ſcruple / of gaules the way<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ghte a dram<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and a half: temper all theſe thin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ges to gether / and geue it to the infante to drynke.</p>
               <p>¶ Item take the ſede of ſorrell / and beate it / then temper it to gether with the yowlke of a roſted egge / and geue that to the chylde to eate.</p>
               <pb n="lxi" facs="tcp:16499:57" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <p>¶ Item take a gaulle / &amp; beate it to pouder / then ſethe it in water with this water / tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per barley meale / or the meale of millium / &amp; make a plaſter of it / the which laye vnto the chyldes belly. ¶ Yf this profet not: take of acatia &amp; ſeruſe of eche a dram<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / of opium the wayght of an halfe peny / of ſugre a dram<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / &amp; of all theſe tempered to gether / make a ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitary of the length of a fynger &amp; an halfe the thyckeneſſe of two wheten ſtrawys twy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ned to gether / &amp; the ſame co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ueys into the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fantes foundament / &amp; it ſhall ſeaſe the flyxe.</p>
               <p>¶ Ite<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> yf that that cometh fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the chyld / be whytyſſhe / then take of nutte megges the wayght of the .viij. parte of a dram<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / and of whyte fra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>kencenſe a ſcruple / the which tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per it with the iuyce of a quynſe / and geue it to the chylde to drynke.</p>
               <p>¶ Item take an ounce of ſafrane / of myr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rhe / a quartar of an ounce and temper them with redde wyne / makyng of it a plaſter / the which laye vnto the chyldes bellye.</p>
               <p>Item take the meale of barleye / temper it with the iuyce of plantan and a lyttell vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gre / and make it plaſterwyſe / and laye it to the chyldes belly.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:16499:58" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <p>¶ Item take the iuyce of centinodium and the whyte of an egge: and temper them toge<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther / to the whiche adde the pouder of dryed red roſes / the pouder of hematites / maſtyc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke frankencenſe / bole armenyacke / ſanguis draconis and pſida: of all theſe myxed to ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther make a plaſter / and laye it to the infan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes bellye.</p>
               <p>¶ Item to waſſhe the chylde with the wa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter in the which be ſoden leues of red rooſes is very good. Item take the iuyce of confery and the iuyce of plantayne the more and the leſſe / and in this put claye of an olde furnyſe or ouen / and make of it a plaſter / and laye it to the chyldes bellye.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="illness">
               <head>¶ To vnlooſe the chylde beynge bounden.</head>
               <p>Yf the chylde be ſo bounde / that it can not ſege: then make a ſuppoſitary of hony ſoden tyll it be harde and maſſye / and let the ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſitary be of the length of your lyttell fynger / &amp; the byggeneſſe of two wheteſtrays bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de to gether / then dyppe it into oyle and conuey it into the chyldes foundament.</p>
               <p>¶ Item lykewyſe ye maye make a ſuppoſi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tary of the ſtalke and rote of betes / or els of
<pb n="lxii" facs="tcp:16499:58" rendition="simple:additions"/>the rote called oreſſe or flowre de luce rote / made of the quantite before ſpoken of / &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueyed into the ſyttynge place of the chylde.</p>
               <p>¶ Item to geue to the infant as much ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny as a peaze to drynke &amp; to rubbe the bellye a lyttell / and to ſople it with a pece of wooll dypped in oyle / or dypped in bulles galle / &amp; layde to the nauell. Item ye maye geue vnto the nource a medycyne whiche hathe vertue to vnbynde and looſe / and the next day after let the chylde ſucke her / and it wyll looſe al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo the chylde.</p>
               <p>¶ Item take of mouſe dounge half a dram<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and temper it with the fatte in the kydnees of a goote / &amp; make a ſuppoſitor of the ſame. Item take of ſmall mallowes / of greate mal<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lowes of eche an handefull of fenegreke and lynſede of eche an handefull / of holycke two ounces / of fygges the nomber of .x. ſethe all theſe to gether in water / &amp; then ſtampe them in a morter / and put vnto it of butter and of hennes grece .ij. ounces / and of ſafrane one ſcruple / and make a plaſter of it vppon a lynnen clothe of the thyckeneſſe of a ſtrawe / and laye it to the chyldes bellye a daye and a nyghte.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:16499:59"/>
               <p>¶ Yf this moue not the belly / then take of aloes one dram<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / of eleborus bothe niger and albus of eche .xv. graynes / beate theſe to pou<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>der / then temper them with thre ſponefulles of the iuyce of walwort or of oxe gall: in this licoure dyppe wooll / and laye it to the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell the bredthe of a hande / and bynde it to the place.</p>
               <p>¶ Item take the iuyce of wallwurte and of myll meale and ſethe thoſe to gether / tyll they be thycke / then make a plaſter thereof / and laye it to the bellye benethe the nauell.</p>
               <p>Item take two handefulles of redde roſes and putte them in to a bagge of foure fyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers bredthe / then ſethe it in the water wher<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>in ſmythes quenche theyr hote yron / putting to it a lyttell vynegre / the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> take out the bagge agayne / and wrynge it a lyttell / then laye it to the chyldes ſtomacke. Item to annoynte the chyldes bellye with butter / the whiche hath ſtyped and ſtande longe in the rynde of walnuttes / is very good.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="illness">
               <head>¶ Remedye for the crampe or diſtention of the membres.</head>
               <p>Yf it chaunſe that the infant be taken with
<pb n="lxiii" facs="tcp:16499:59" rendition="simple:additions"/>the deſeaſe / called the crampe / the which for the moſt parte co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth of indigeſtion and of the wekeneſſe of the powre attractyue: &amp; ſpe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cially in ſuch chyldren the which be very fat and moyſte / then ſhall ye annoynte the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fant with the oyle of blewe flowre de lyce / or elles whyte lyllyes / other the oyle of rue. Yf the crampe take the chylde whylſte it ſtret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth forth the armes / legges / and other me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bres (as we be wont in gapyng or yanynge) then let it be bathed and waſſhed in water / in the whyche tapſus barbatus is foden in / or elles annoynted with the oyle of violet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes / and the oyle of ſwete almons tempered to gether / and yf the chylde be in great heate annoynte hym with the oyle of violettes / or with oyle olyfe / te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pered with a lyttell whyte wexe / and alſo powre on the chyldes heade the oyle of violettes.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="illness">
               <head>¶ Remedy for the coughe and diſtillation of the heade.</head>
               <p>Sometymes the chylde is ſore encombred with the coughe and with diſtillatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> or run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nynge of humours oute of the heade / to the noſe / the mouthe and the breſt: the which he
<pb facs="tcp:16499:60" rendition="simple:additions"/>ſhall remedye thus: Fyrſt powre warme wa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter on the chyldes heade holdynge it a fote &amp; a halfe from the chyldes heade / and ſo do co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tynuallye the ſpace of halfe an houre / and in the meane whyle put a lyttell honye on the chyldes tonge to chawe vpon / then put your fynger in to the chyldes mouth / and depreſſe or holde downe the ynner moſte parte or the rote of the tunge nexte to the throte / to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoke the chylde to vomyte / and to voyde the groſſe and viſcous humours which be cauſe of this yll.</p>
               <p>¶ Item take gumme arabicke / gumme dra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gagant / the ſede of quynces / the iuyce of lyco<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ryſe / and ſugre penedium: all this beaten to<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gether / geue euery daye to the chylde a quan<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tite of it with mylke newe mylked. Item take ſwete almons and blanch them / &amp; then beate them in a morter / and then ſethe them with the iuyce of fenell / or els the water ther<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>of: of this decoction geue to the chylde at eue<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nynge and mornynge. Item the water of fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nell tempered with mylke / and ſo dronken / is very good.</p>
               <p>¶ And yf it ſo be that the coughe haue ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſperat and made roughe the tounge &amp; the
<pb n="lxiiii" facs="tcp:16499:60" rendition="simple:additions"/>rofe of the mouthe / then take of the ſedes of rydonium .ij. ſponefulles: bruſe them a lyttel and ſtype them in warme water the ſpace of two or thre houres: then ſtrayne the vyſcoſe and groſſe water fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> them throughe a ſtray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner / and that remayneth / frye it to gether in a fryenge panne with ſugre penidium &amp; the oyle of ſwete almons therof makyng an ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctuarium: the which geue vnto the chylde to receaue: yf the chylde haue great heate with the coughe / then adde vnto the ſame electua<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rie the iuyce of a ſwete pome granate.</p>
               <p>¶ Item agaynſt the coughe &amp; ouer muche heate: take of whyte popye / and dragagant two dram<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s / of the granes of Gowards .iiij. dram<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s / and beate all theſe to gether / &amp; geue of it to the chylde with the water in whiche reaſons haue ben ſoden.</p>
               <p>¶ Item take reaſons / and takynge out the ſede or graynes of it: ſethe them to gether with water in a fryenge panne / ſo that they burne not to the botom of the pan / then take it from the fyre / and beate it well in a morter temperynge there with all ſugre penidium / and geue of this in the mornynge &amp; euenyng to the chylde.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:16499:61" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <p>¶ Agayne yf the coughe come of a colde cauſe / then take a lyttell myrrhe beaten to powder / and temper it with a quantite of warmed hony and the oyle of ſwete almon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des / and of this geue vnto the chylde.</p>
               <p>¶ Farthermore the nourſe muſte auoyde all ſuch thynges the whiche maye engender coughe: as vynegre / ouer muche ſalted mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes / nuttes / and all ſharpe thynges. Alſo ſhe muſte annoynt the chyldes breſt with butter and with dialtheas.</p>
               <p>¶ Item for the coughe: take reaſons / and frye them in a fryenge panne / then ſtampe them in a mortar / and to that adde as much of ſugre penidium / with a lyttell oyle of vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lettes / and make an electuarye of theſe / and geue to the chyld the mountenaunce of a ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell nutte.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="illness">
               <head>¶ Remedye for ſhorte wynde.</head>
               <p>Manye tymes chaunſeth alſo to infantes difficultie of brethynge or ſhorte wyndeneſſe / the which to remedye: take lyne ſede / &amp; beate it / and geue it on the childe with hony: but yf the deſeaſe encreaſe on the chylde / &amp; that the wyne pipes in maner ſeme ſtopped / then an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noynte
<pb n="lxv" facs="tcp:16499:61" rendition="simple:additions"/>well the eares / and all the places about the eares with oyle olyfe / and alſo the tounge for to prouoke vomyte / and then powere a lyttell warme water in to the chyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des mouthe / and geue to it a lyttell lyneſede tempered with hony and beaten / made after the faſhyon of an electuarye.</p>
               <p>¶ Item yf the chylde haue beſydes this al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo the flyx: then geue vnto it the ſyrupe of myrche decocte with hony / other elles dates ſoden with mylke / and the meale of wheate.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="illness">
               <head>¶ Agaynſt wheles or bladders on the tounge.</head>
               <p>Item ſometymes happeneth to chyldren wheles and blyſters on theyr tounges and mouth / whiche thinge cometh of the ſharpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and egreneſſe of the nources mylke / the mouthe &amp; tounge of the infant beynge ſo tender that the leſt thing that toucheth it / ſhall offende it / wherefore beſydes that it is great payne to the chylde thus to be blyſtered by the egreneſſe of the mylke it is alſo verye pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rellous &amp; dangerous / for ſuch wheles which be not rype and ſeme blacke / betoken death / whiche yf they be whyte or yelowyſhe / then they be of leſſe parell. Agaynſt this yll: take
<pb facs="tcp:16499:62" rendition="simple:additions"/>violettes / roſes / and xylocaracta / and tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per all theſe beatynge them to gether / &amp; laye of it vpon the blyſters.</p>
               <p>¶ Ite<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> take the iuyce of letuſe / the iuyce of ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latrum / and the iuyce of purcelayne / whiche when they be well commyxte and tempered to gether / annoynt there with the whelkes. And yf the foreſayde blyſterres or whelkes be blackyſſhe / then adde to the foreſayde my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces lycoryſe beaten to pouder.</p>
               <p>¶ Item yf the ſame be very moyſt / then take myrrhe / galles / the ryne of fra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>kencenſe: bete them well to gether / and temper them with hony / and annoynte the chyldes tonge there with.</p>
               <p>¶ Item take the iuyce of ſharpe mulberies other els of vnrype grapes / which is called vergeus / &amp; with that annoynt the tonge. Ite<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it is verye good to waſſhe the tunge with wyne / &amp; then to ſtrewe vpon it the pouder of galles / or elles of the barke or rynde of fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kencenſe.</p>
               <p>¶ Yf ye wyll haue a quyckar medicine in operation &amp; a ſharper / then take bole arme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nye / pſida and ſumach of eche .iij. dram<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s / al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo of galles .ij. drin<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of alome one dram<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: all
<pb n="lxvi" facs="tcp:16499:62" rendition="simple:additions"/>theſe beate to gether &amp; ſerche them throught a ſerchar / &amp; ſtrewe that pouder on the blyſter<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>res. Ite<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> yf this wheles be reddyſhe &amp; cauſe muche ſpettyll to gather to gyther in that place / then lette the nourſe vſe ſuche thinges which are moyſt &amp; colde / and let her chawe in her mouthe verye ſmall a fewe fatches / of the which laye on the infa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes mouth &amp; tu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge.</p>
               <p>¶ Ite<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> amidum te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pered to gether with roſe water / &amp; put on the chyldes tunge / is good. Ite<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> take the iuyce of pome granates / the iuy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ce of quynces / or the iuyce of orynges / &amp; do of this on the chyldes tunge in lyke maner / but yf the wheles or blyſters be ſomewhat ye<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowyſh then to theſe iuyces ſpoken of before adde the iuyce of lettuce &amp; of purcelayne.</p>
               <p>¶ But yf the wheles ſeme whytyſhe / then take of myrre / &amp; of ſafrane / of eche one dram<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / of ſugre candy .ij. dram<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s / and beate theſe to pouder and laye of it on the wheles and the tunge.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="illness">
               <head>¶ Of exulceration or clefture, chappynge, or chynynge of the mouthe.</head>
               <p>Sometymes by reaſon of the hardeneſſe of the nources pappes the chyldes lyppes &amp;
<pb facs="tcp:16499:63" rendition="simple:additions"/>mouthe be exulcerat hauynge in manner of cleftes and chynnes in them and in this caſe take tozed wooll / and dyppe it in the iuyce of plantayne / or elles in butter molten / or in freſſhe hens greſe euery of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> beyng warme and with this annoynte the mouth and lyp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pes of the chylde.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="illness">
               <head>¶ Of Apoſtumation and runnyng of the eares.</head>
               <p>When that humours and matter yſſueth out of the eares which properly commeth of aboundant humours in all the body / &amp; moſt ſpetially in the head / the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> take a peſe of wool / and dyppe it in hony mixt with redde wyne / to the which is put alſo a lyttell quantite of alome beaten to pouder / or of ſafrane / then make of the ſame as it ware a tente / and put it in the childes eare / &amp; when the wooll hath ſucked and drawen to it the humour and fyl thyneſſe of the eare / then take it out / and put in newe / and if that / the which commeth out of the eare be as matter / then take of ſoden hony and tempered with water / put of it in to the eares / or elles take the pouder of gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les temperynge it with vynegre / and do lyke wyſe.</p>
               <pb n="lxvii" facs="tcp:16499:63" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <p>¶ But yf the chylde haut greate payne &amp; dolor by wyndyneſſe / ventoſyte and the hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours in this place / then ſethe organnye or myrrhe with oyle olyfe and ſo beyng warme put of it in to the eares.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="illness">
               <head>¶ Of Appoſtumation in the heade.</head>
               <p>Yf there be any appoſtume engendred in the heade (whiche many tymes chaunſeth) the whiche cauſethe the cheekes and eyes to be greatelye payned / and the eye ſight to waxe wannyſſhe or tawnye / then muſt be applyed ſuche thynges whiche maye refrigerat and coole the braynes: as take of the iuyce of go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes and the iuyce of ſolatrum / and the iuyce of purcelayne / and temper them with the oyle of roſes / in this dyp a peſe of wooll and laye it to the head / and as ofte as it wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>xeth drye / dippe it agayne / and lykewyſe laye it to the heade.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="illness">
               <head>¶ Of the ſwellynge or bolnyng of the eyes.</head>
               <p>Agaynſt ſwellynge &amp; bolnynge of the eyes: take licium / and temper it with womans mylke / and put of it into the chyldes eye / and bynde it to the place with fyne and ſofte lyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nen
<pb facs="tcp:16499:64" rendition="simple:additions"/>clothe / then afterwarde waſſhe the eyes with water in whiche camomell and baſyll haue ben ſoden in. Yf that in this ſwellynge the eyes be not redde / neyther the browes ſwollen / then take myrrhe / aloes / ſafrane / &amp; the leues of roſes / and temper all theſe / and ſtype them in olde wyne: and bynde it to the thyldes eyes with ſome lynnen clothe / &amp; into the childes noſe put a quantite of ambre diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolued in womans mylke.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="illness">
               <head>¶ Of the ſcum or whyte of the eye.</head>
               <p>Agaynſt the ſcum or whyte of the eye which for the moſt parte happeneth to chyldre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowe ouer much cryeng &amp; wepynge: take the iuyce of ſolatrum / and droppe of the ſame in to the chyldes eye / and yf by the ſame chanſe the vayne of the eyes wexe reddyſſhe / or be ſwollen / then annoynt them with the ſame iuyce.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="illness">
               <head>¶ Agaynſt immoderat heate or the feuer.</head>
               <p>Yf the infant be in great &amp; vehement heate contrary to nature / the whiche is called a fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer. Fyrſt it ſhalbe the nources parte to eate and vſe ſuche thynges the whiche coole and
<pb n="lxviii" facs="tcp:16499:64" rendition="simple:additions"/>moyſte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Alſo to geue vnto the infant of theſe thynges folowynge: the iuyce of pome gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate / the water of gourdes / ſugre / with a lyt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tell camphere myxed here with all / tempered well to gether. Ite<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it is very good to prouo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke it to ſweiyng. ¶ Ite<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> take of the iuyce of worme wood / of plantayne / malows / &amp; ſyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grene / and temper them all to gether / in the whiche alſo myxte barly meale / and make a plaſter of all theſe / and laye it to the chyldes breſte. Ite<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> take the oyle of roſes &amp; the oyle of poplar / &amp; myxte them to gether with this oyntment beyng colde / annoynt the chyldes forehead / the temples / the armes / the ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des about the wryſtes &amp; pulces / &amp; the fete about the ancles. Ite<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> take of barlye meale and of dryed roſes &amp; poudered / &amp; temper theſe with the water of roſes &amp; the water of endyue / &amp; make therof a plaſter / the which laye to the chyldes breſt.</p>
               <p>¶ Alſo as often as the chylde is waſſhed / let it be done with water in whiche is ſoden ſuch thynges whiche coole / as lectuſe / purce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>layne / endyue / plantane / and ſuch other.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="illness">
               <head>¶ Agaynſt frettynge or knawynge in the belly.</head>
               <pb facs="tcp:16499:65" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <p>Yf the chylde be vexed with frettynge and knawynge in the belly / the which thynge ye ſhall know by the immoderat cryeng of the chylde / and that it turneth from one ſyde to another with greate cryenge / then ſhall you take warme water / oyle olyfe / and a lyttell waxe / temperynge them to gether / and here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in dyppe a peſe of wooll / and there with ſoke the chyldes bellye oftentymes.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="illness">
               <head>¶ Agaynſtc ſwellynge of the bodye.</head>
               <p>When the chyldes bodye or any parte ther of is ſwollen and puffed vp / then take the toppes of elder tree / and of walworte: and ſethe them in white wyne / &amp; therein lap the infante / ſpetially yf it be not take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with ouer greate heate / but yf ſo be that with ſwellyng in the heade the bellye be ſwollen alſo / then take myrrhe / aloes epaticus / &amp; ſafrane / and beate them all to gether / and temper them with the iuyce of beanes / and laye it to the thyldes heade.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="illness">
               <head>¶ Agaynſt often ſneeſynge.</head>
               <p>Sometymes the infantes be ſore troubled and vexed with often ſtarnutatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and ſnee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſynge
<pb n="lxix" facs="tcp:16499:65" rendition="simple:additions"/>/ which thynge yf it come of the appo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtume in the head: then ſhal ye miniſter ſuch thynges to the heade whiche refrigerat and coole / whether it be oyles / oyntmentes / iuy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of herbes or other thynges. Yf this come of anye other cauſe then of appoſtume / then take baſilicum / be it grene or drye / and put of the iuyce or pouder of it into the childes noſe but yf this ſneeſynge come and begyn with heate / &amp; that the chyldes eyes ſeme as they grewe in warde for payne of this ſneeſynge / then laye to thyldes heade the leaues of pur celayne / or gowarde cut in thynne peces and tempered with the oyle of rooſes and barley meale / and alſo the yowlke of an egge.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="illness">
               <head>¶ Of whelkes in the body and the cure.</head>
               <p>Theſe whelkes yf they appeare blacke vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon the body / they ſygnify parell of lyfe / and ſo muche the more the greater quantite that there is of them / but yf they ſeme whytyſhe or reddyſhe / it is no parell / &amp; maye eaſelye be cured: wherfore take the leues of the red roſe the leues of myrtylles &amp; of tamariſcus / and ſethe theſe in water / and in that water wette a lynne<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> cloth / &amp; ſoke there with the whelkes.
<pb facs="tcp:16499:66"/>Ite<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> like wyſe it is good to annoynt the ſame with the oyle of roſes / of myrtylles / &amp; tama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſcus. Yf the whelke be whyte or reddyſhe / then let them be rype / before ye miniſter any thyng to them / &amp; when they be open &amp; begyn to matterye / then annoynte them with the oyntemente of ceruſe. Item it ſhalbe verye good for the ſame purpoſe to waſh the ſame whelkes with mulſum &amp; hydromell / in whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che ſalt peter hath ben ſtyped &amp; dyſſolued.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="illness">
               <head>¶ Agaynſt ſwellyng of the coddes.</head>
               <p>Manye tymes chaunſeth to chyldren (tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowe ouer much cryenge) ſwellynge aboute the coddes / &amp; ſometymes burſtenneſſe &amp; ſwel lynge in the ynner parte of the thyghes. Againſt this yll take the ſede of ameos: bete it &amp; temper it with the yowike of an egge / &amp; laye it to the ſwellynge or burſtenneſte / and thereto bynde it with ſome gentell lynnen clothe. Item take bytter lupynes &amp; myrre / and ſtype them in wyne / and ſethe them to gether makynge hereof a plaſter / the whiche laye to the greued parte.</p>
               <p>¶ Item take of alome .xiii. dram<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s / of gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les .xi. dram<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s: beate them / and ſethe them to
<pb n="lxx" facs="tcp:16499:66"/>gether in redde wyne / tyl it be thycke / of this laye on the greued place / holdyng alſo vpon it a ſponge dypped in water / myxt with vy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>negre / oftentymes renuynge the ſame when it is waſted. Alſo you maye take the afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſayde decoction / puttynge vnto it a quantite of ſyſe / and ſethynge them to gether / &amp; make a plaſter of it / &amp; ſpredde it on a lynnen cloth / and ſo bynde it to the place / and often tymes to renue it.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="illness">
               <head>¶ Agaynſte ſwellynge of the nauell.</head>
               <p>Alſo ſometymes the chyldes nauell ſwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth / &amp; ſpetially ſtreyte after the byrth when it is cutte / for this take ſpyke celtyke / whiche ſome call mary mawdelyne flowre / the whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che women vſe to put in lye / &amp; ſethe it in the oyle of ſeſamu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> myxed with turpentyne / then in this dyp wooll / &amp; laye it on the place the thyckeneſſe of a fynger.</p>
               <p>¶ But yf ſo be that this ſwellyng come of ouer muche cryenge / cough / or of a ſtrooke or fall / then take lupynes &amp; the pouder of fayre olde lynnen clothe burnt to pouder / and tem<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>per theſe with red wyne / &amp; then in this dyp a peſe of towe / and laye it to the nauell.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="illness">
               <pb facs="tcp:16499:67" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <head>¶ Agaynſt vnſlepyneſſe.</head>
               <p>Agaynſte vnſlepyneſſe / that is / when the chylde is deſtitute and wanteth his due and naturall reſte / all the whyle cryeng and we<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinge / for this take the ſtalkes of popye / and the ſede with all / and temper it with the oyle of lectuſe and the oyle of popye / all theſe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ynge myxt to gether / bynde them with ſome lynnen clothe to the forehead &amp; temples of the chylde.</p>
               <p>¶ But yf this vnſlepyneſſe come of the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>purite and ylneſſe of the nourſes mylke (as many tymes it doth) then take of the oyle of violettes / and put vnto it a lyttell quantite of vynegre / and of this lycoure drop often ty<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mes in to the chyldes noſethrylles / or elles take the oyle of rooſes / and temper it with the iuyce of letuce / and therewith annoynte the heade and ſtomacke of the chylde / &amp; far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſe that the nourſes mylke be amended.</p>
               <p>¶ Item take the ſyrupe of whyte popye / &amp; geue of it to the chyld to drynke / annoynting the foreheade and temples with the oyle of violettes / in whiche is put a lyttell quantite of ſafrane and of oppium.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="illness">
               <head>¶ Agaynſte yexynge.</head>
               <pb n="lxxi" facs="tcp:16499:67" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <p>Agaynſt yexynge: take a nutte of ynde / and beate it / temperynge it with ſugre / and geue it to the chylde to eate: this yexynge cometh other of ouer muche meate / or for lacke of meate and emptyneſſe of the ſtomacke.</p>
               <p>¶ As often as it commeth by the aboun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance of meate &amp; coldeneſſe of the ſtomacke / then annoynte the ſtomacke with the oyle of bays warmed / other els laye to the ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macke a plaſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>r made of the ſede of dyll bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten and tempered with the iuyce of myntes.</p>
               <p>¶ But yf it come by defecte and lacke of meate and emptyneſſe of the ſtomacke / take the oyle of violettes / or of rooſes / or the iuyce of endyue / or of anye other ſuche herbes / the which haue power to infrigidat &amp; coole / and temper the ſame with womans mylke / and annoynte therewith the chyldes ſtomacke. Alſo geue the chylde to feade vpon mylke &amp; other good and holſome thynges to ſuppe neyther paſſe not greately / though the chyld reiecte and vomyte vp agayne that the whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che it receaueth / for ſoo muche euer wyll re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mayne in the ſtomacke that ſhalbe ſufficient to ſuſtayne it and to moyſten it.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="illness">
               <head>¶ Of yerkeneſſe or appetyte to vomyte.</head>
               <pb facs="tcp:16499:68" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <p>Agaynſt ouer muche appetyte to vomyte / bete .iiij. graynes of cloues / and geue it to the chylde. Item take of maſtycke / whyte fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kenſence / and the leues of the redde rooſe / ſo muche as ſhalbe ſufficient / and all theſe bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten to gether / temper them with the iuyce of myntes / and make a plaſter of it layenge it to the chyldes ſtomacke: but yf the chyldes vomytynge be very vehement / then put vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to theſe foreſayd thynge a quantite of vyne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gre.</p>
               <p>¶ Item take fyne meale / and bake it ſo hote / tyll it ware browne / then beate it to pouder agayne / puttynge it in to vynegre / &amp; to theſe adde the yowlke of an egge harde roſted / maſtycke / frankenſence / &amp; gumme arabycke / and temper all theſe with the iuyce of myn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes / makynge of it a plaſter the which lay to the childes ſtomacke / &amp; to the childes mouth holde a warme toſte of breade.</p>
               <p>¶ Cauſes of this yll be .iii. the fyrſte / yf the childe haue taken more mylke then it is able to concocte &amp; digeſte: the ſeconde / yf the nour<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſes mylke be ouer thynne / wateryſh / and flu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yſhe: the thyrd / yf the ſame mylke be impure
<pb n="lxxii" facs="tcp:16499:68" rendition="simple:additions"/>feculent and corrupte: theſe cauſes pronoke vomyte / and ſpetiallye yf the chylde alſoo haue a weake and wateryſſhe ſtomacke / wherfore ye muſt helpe the infant after this maner: fyrſte lette the chylde ſucke leſſe then it dyd before / and then alſoo marke that the whiche the chylde dothe perbrake / whether it ſauer ſharpelye lyke vynegre / and that it be whytyſſhe: for yf it be ſoo / then take of whyte frankenſence .viij. graynes / of dryed rue .xx. graynes / beate theſe to pouder / and geue it to the chylde to drynke / with the ſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupe of redde rooſes.</p>
               <p>¶ Or elles lette the nourſe chawe comyn / and ſo put it into the chyldes mouthe / geue alſoo of the ſyrupe of pome granates / with the pouder of drye myntes to the chylde.</p>
               <p>¶ Item take of xiloaloes one dram<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / of gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les .x. graynes: beate all thoſe to pouder / tem<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>per it with the ſyrupe of rooſes / puttynge to it a lyttell of nutmegges / and geue of this to the chylde to drynke euer before it ſucke / alſoo to the ſtomacke of the chylde laye this plaſter.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:16499:69" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <p>¶ Take maſtycke / accatia / xiloaloes / galles / whyte frankencenſe / toſted breade / of eche lyke much / beate them to gether puttynge to of redde rooſes and temperynge it with the ſyrupe of rooſes / and ſo laye it to the chyldes ſtomacke.</p>
               <p>¶ But yf it ſo be that the perbrakynge of the chylde ſauer not after the faſhyon of vy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>negre / but after ſome other ſo wre ſauour / &amp; that it be not whytyſhe / but pale &amp; grayeſſhe then geue it the iuyce of quynces / and laye this plaſter vnto the chyldes ſtomacke: take barley meale / wylde mulderyes / and pſida / beate all theſe to gether / and temper it with rooſe water / and laye it to the chyldes ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macke.</p>
               <p>¶ And farthermore yf the childes ſtomacke be ſome what wateryſhe and ſlowe in dige<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion / then annoynte it with the water of ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes / in the which muſke hath ben dyſſolued / or elles the water of myrtylles: and geue it to drynke the iuyce of quynces with a lyttell cloues and ſugre / or with a ſcruple of nutte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>megges / there with tempered and myxed.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="illness">
               <head>¶ Agaynſt fearefull and terrible dreames.</head>
               <pb n="lxxvii" facs="tcp:16499:69" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <p>
                  <gap reason="missing" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page missing〉</desc>
                  </gap> uers other thinges there be which might be here reherſed / but this ſhalbe ſuffitient.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="illness">
               <head>¶ Conſumption or pynynge awaye of the body.</head>
               <p>When the infante falleth awaye / and the fleſſhe rebateth remaynynge nothynge but as it ware ſkynne and bone / and thereby the chylde waxeth ſyckely / then let the infant be often bathed in water / in which hath ben ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den the head &amp; the fete of a ramme / ſo longe tyll the fleſſhe parte frome the bones of his owne accorde / and euery tyme that the chyld commeth forth of the bathe / fyrſt let it be wy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ped and dryed cleane / &amp; then annoynt it with this oyntmente: take freſſ he butter / oyle of violettes / or oyle of rooſes / of eche .ii. dram<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s / of ſwyneſgrece .vi. dram<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s / of whyte wex .iiij. dram<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s: melt all theſe thynges to gether / and make an oyntment of it / annoyntynge there with the chyldes body.</p>
               <p>¶ Item take whyte waxe / ſwenes grece / ſhepes tallowe / freſſhe butter / melt all theſe thinges to gether / &amp; ſtrayne them / making of it an oyntme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to annoynt the chyld withall.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="illness">
               <head>¶ Of laſſitude, weryneſſe, or heuyneſſe of the chyldes hodye.</head>
               <pb facs="tcp:16499:70" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <p>Sometymes it chaunſeth that the chyldes membres of the body be ſo feable / as though it hath the palſye / ſo that with that partes of the bodye the chylde can not helpe it ſelfe / neyther can it lefte vp the handes / armes / ne ſtande on the fete / yf the chylde haue this dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeaſe whylſt it ſucketh / then let the nourſe be comforted and ſtrengthned with ſuch thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges the whiche haue vertue to heate and to drye. Alſo let the nourſe fede onely on roſted or fryed meate / &amp; that ſhe forbare fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> mylke / fyſſhe / and harde or ſalt poudred fleſſhe.</p>
               <p>¶ Farthermore let not the nourſe vſe any watered wyne / or myxed: &amp; let her bathe the childe euer before that ſhe geue it ſucke / after annoyntynge it with the oyle of caſtorium / or the oyle of coſtum / &amp; let the chylde drynke euerye daye a quantite of this electuarye fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowyng: Take wyld mynt / cynamome / cum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myn / drye roſes / maſticke / fenugreke / valeria<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ne / ameum / doronicum / zedoarium / cloues / ſaunders / xiloaloes / of eche a dram<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / of muſke halfe a dram<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / beate all thoſe to pouder / &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fycte them with clarifyed wyne / makynge thereof an electuarye / of the whyche euerye daye geue vnto the chylde the, iiij. parte of a
<pb n="lxxviii" facs="tcp:16499:70" rendition="simple:additions"/>dram<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to drynke. Yf the chylde haue this dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeaſe in euerye parte of his bodye / then take an ounce of wexe / and a dram<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of euforbium / temper them to gether with oyle olyfe / and make hereof a plaſter / and laye it to the ray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of the backe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="illness">
               <head>¶ Of trymblynge of the bodye and the membres of the bodye.</head>
               <p>Yf the chylde happen to be vexed with trym<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>blynge and quakyng of the bodye or the par<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes thereof / ſo that ye feare that ſhryncklyng of the parte / or that the fallynge ſyckeneſſe ſholde enſue / then remeady it after this mea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes: take the oyle of rooſes / and the oyle of nardus / and temper them to gether / war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mynge it / and there with annoyntynge the backe boke or raynes and the other ſhakyng membres / ye maye alſo take any other oyle / the whiche hathe vertue to warme and cale<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fye / as the oyle of bays / and ſuche other. Yf thou can not cure it by this meanes / then demaunde farther counceill of the phyſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyons.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="illness">
               <head>¶ Of the ſtone.</head>
               <pb facs="tcp:16499:71" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <p>Yf the chylde be emcombred with the ſtone or with anye other thynge the whiche maye lette, and ſtoppe the vryne / the whiche maye be knowen by theſe tokens: Fyrſt yf he haue the ſtra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gury / yf it be prouoked often to pyſſe and yet can do but lyttell at once / and that with greate payne and dolour / yf the vryne be thynne and clere / and alſo (beynge a man chylde) yf the prycke be euer ſtandynge: all which thynges ye ſhall remedye thus:</p>
               <p>¶ Fyrſt bathe the chylde in water wherin is decocte malous / holyoke / lynſede / and pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritorye / then geue it to drynke ſome ſuche thinge which hath qualite to prouoke vryne and alſo when the nourſe layeth it to ſleape / let her annoynte the pryuie partes with oyle and geue the chylde to drynke the water of mulberyes with mylke / or otherwyſe: take the bloude of a gote / and the powder of a burnt ſcorpion / with the oyle of ſcorpions / or the oyle of whyte lyllyes tempered plaſter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wyſe / and laye it to the chyldes bellye aboue the pryuie membres.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="illness">
               <head>¶ Of google eyes or lokynge a ſquynt.</head>
               <p>Yf the chylde haue google eyes / or that it
<pb n="lxxix" facs="tcp:16499:71" rendition="simple:additions"/>loke a ſquynt / then fyrſt ſet the cradel in ſuch a place / that the lyght maye come directelye and ryght in the chyldes face / neyther in the one ſyde / neyther in the other / neyther aboue the heade / leſte it torne the ſyghte after the lyght. Alſo marke / on whiche ſyde that the eyes do gogle / and let the lyghte come vnto it on the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trary ſyde / ſo to retorne the ſyght. And in the nyght ſeaſon ſet a candell on the contrarye ſyde / ſo that by this meane the go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glynge of the eyes maye be retorned to the ryghte place. And farther it ſhall be good to hange clothes of diuers and freſhe coloures on the contrary ſyde / and ſpetially of the co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loure of lyght grene / or yelowe / for the chylde ſhall haue pleaſure to beholde theſe ſtrange coloures / and in retornynge the eye ſyghte towarde ſuche thynges / it ſhalbe occaſion to rectifye the ſyght agayne: and this ſhall be ſufficient for this tyme of the dyſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of chyldren / after they be borne makynge here an ende of this ſeconde boke.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div n="3" type="book">
            <pb facs="tcp:16499:72" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>THE THIRDE BOKE.</head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>¶ Of ſuche thynges the which ſhalbe en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treated of in this thyrde boke. ¶ Cap .i.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N theſe two precedente bokes we haue ſufficientelye for this tyme declared ſuch thinges the which are wont to happen vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to women before theyr labor / in theyr labor / &amp; alſo after theyr labor / and far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of ſuch infirmities and deſeaſes / which are wont to vexe the infant after it is delyue<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>red into this wordle / with competent reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyes for the ſame.</p>
               <p>¶ And here in this thyrde boke (by the leaue of god) ſhall brefelye be declared ſuche thyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges whiche maye farther or hynder the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception of man / whiche as it maye be by dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers meanes letted and hyndered / ſo alſo by many other wayes it maye be farthered and amended. Alſo to knowe by certayne ſygnes and tokens whether the woman be concea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued or no / &amp; whether the conception be male or female / and finally certayne remedies and medycynes to farther and helpe conceptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / &amp; ſo to conclude this ſmall tracte or treatyce.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <pb n="lxxx" facs="tcp:16499:72" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <head>¶ Of conception, &amp; howe many wayes it maye be hyndered or letted. ¶ Cap .ii.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Here is nothyng vnder heauen which ſo manifeſtly &amp; playnlye doth declare &amp; ſhewe the mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifice<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t myghtyneſſe of that om<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nipote<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t lyuing god / as doth the perpetuall and continuall generation &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception of lyuynge thynges here in earth / by the whiche is ſaued / proroged / &amp; augmented the kynd of al thinges. And where that this almyghty lorde &amp; creator hath ſo inſtitute &amp; ordeyned / that no ſyngular thynge in it ſelfe (here vpon the earth) ſholde contynually re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mayne &amp; abyde / yet hath he geuen from the begynnyng and inſtincted ſuch a power and vertue vnto theſe mortall creatures / that they maye engender and produce other lyke thinges vnto them ſelfe / &amp; vnto theyr owne ſunilitude / in the which alway is ſaued the ſede of poſterite / were not this prouiſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> had by almyghtye god / the nature &amp; kynde of all maner of thinges wold ſone peryſh &amp; com to an ende / the which vertue &amp; power of genera<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> many times doth halt &amp; miſſe / by defect &amp; the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trary diſpoſitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in the partes genera<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:16499:73" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <p>As ye maye euidentlye ſee in the ſowynge of corne and all other maner of ſeade / ſo that there be in all maner of generation thre prin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cipal partes co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>curre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to the ſame: the ſower / the ſcade ſowen / and the receptacle or place receauynge and contaynynge the ſeade. Yf there be faute in any of theſe thre / then ſhall there neuer be due generation / vnto ſuche tyme as the faute be remoued or amended. The earth vnto all ſeades is as a mother &amp; nource contaynynge / clyppynge and enbra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſynge them in her wombe / feadynge and fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterynge them as the mother doth the chyld in her belly ormatrice / vntyll ſuche tyme as they come vnto the growyth / quantite / &amp; per fection due vnto theyr nature and kynd but yf this ſeade co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ceaued in the bowelles of the earth do not proue or fructifye / then be thou ſure that other there is lette in the ſower / in the ſeade / or elles in the earthe. The earthe maye be ouer wateryſſhe / dankeſſhe / or ouer hote and drye / or elles full of ſtones / grauell / or other rubryſhe / or ful of yll weedes / which maye ſtrangle and choke the good corne in his growynge / alſo the ſede maye be putri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyed / or otherwyſe viciat and corrupted / and
<pb n="lxxxi" facs="tcp:16499:73" rendition="simple:additions"/>ſo the lyfe &amp; ſprete of it vanyſhed awaye and deſtroyed. The ſowar maye vnordynatlye ſtrewe and caſte the ſeade on the earthe. &amp;c. So that yf there be let in none of theſe thre partes concurrent to generation / or that the lettes be remoued &amp; done away / then doubte leſſe will enſue multiplicacion and encreaſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of that kynde / of the which the ſeade co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth / accordyng to the naturall enclination the whiche almyghtye god hathe enplanted and ſet in the kynde of all thynges.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <head>¶ Howe many wayes conception maye be letted. and howe the cauſes maye be knowen. ¶ Cap .iii.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">E</seg>Verye thynge then the whiche doth encreaſe in his kynd muſt fyrſt be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ceaued in the wombe &amp; matrice of the mother / which is apte and conueniente for the receate of ſuch ſeade. And as I ſayde before / as there maye be defecte and lacke in the mo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther receauynge the ſeade / ſoo maye there be faute and defecte in the ſower / &amp; in the ſeade it ſelfe alſo.</p>
               <p>¶ And in woman there maye be foure ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall
<pb facs="tcp:16499:74" rendition="simple:additions"/>cauſes / by the whiche the conception may be impedyte and let: ouer much calidite or heate of the matrice / ouer much coldneſſe / ouer muche humidite or moyſteneſſe / &amp; ouer much dryeneſſe. Any of theſe foure qualitees exceadynge temperancye / maye be ſufficient cauſes to lette due conception.</p>
               <p>¶ Wherfore the ryght excellent phyſitian Hypocra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes in the .v. boke of his Amphoryſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes ſayth: All ſuch women the which haue colde and denſe matrices / can not conceaue / nor ſuch as haue moyſte and wateryſſhe ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>trices can co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ceaue / for the powre of the ſeade is extynguyſhed in it. Alſo hauyng drye ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tryces / conceaue not / for the ſeade peryſſheth for lacke of due nutriment and fode / but that matrice the whiche hath all theſe qualities in temperancye / that is fruytfull / this is Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocrates ſayenge / the which thing alſo may be well perceaued by a famylyer example of the ſowynge of corne.</p>
               <p>¶ For yf it be ſowen in ouer colde places / ſuch as be in the partes of a countrye / called Sithia / and in certayne places of Almayne / or in ſuch places where is contynuall ſnowe or froſte / or where the ſonne doth not ſhyne / 
<pb n="lxxxii" facs="tcp:16499:74" rendition="simple:additions"/>in this places the ſeade or grayne ſowen / wyll neuer come to profe / nor fructyfye / but throughe the vehemente coldeneſſe of the place in the whiche it is conceaued / the lyfe and quyckeneſſe of the grayne is vtterlye de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed and adnyhilat.</p>
               <p>¶ And farther as concernyng ouer muche humidite: Yf ye ſowe your grayne in a fen or maryſſe and watery grounde / the ſeade wyll peryſſhe through the ouer much abounda<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of water whiche extynguyſſheth the lyuely<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and the naturall power of the grayne and ſede.</p>
               <p>¶ Lykewyſe yf it be ſowen in ſuch a coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trye or place where is ouer greate heate / not te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pered with water &amp; rayne / or yf the yere be ſo drye / that there cam no rayne at al to alay the extreme &amp; farue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t heate of the ſonne / then ſhall the ſeade ſowen whyther &amp; drye away / and the power of it be conſumed &amp; burnt.</p>
               <p>¶ Alſo yf it be ſowen in drye places / where neuer commeth rayne / or on the ſande / and grauelye places / in ſuche a place the grayne can neuer take / ne proue / ne be conceaued in it to come to any fruyte or profet.</p>
               <p>¶ Wherefore yf the matrice be diſtempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red
<pb facs="tcp:16499:75" rendition="simple:additions"/>by the exceſſe of any of theſe foure quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties / then muſt ye reduce it agayne to tempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rancie by ſuche remedyes / as I ſhall ſhewe you hereafter. Lykewyſe maye there be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fecte and lacke in the man / as yf the ſeade be ouer hote / the which the woman ſhall feale / as it were burning hote / or to cold the which he ſhall feale / as it were in maner colde as yiſe / or to fluye or thynne. &amp;c. dyuers other other wayes alſo it maye be letted / whyche ſhall not nede here to be reherſed.</p>
               <p>¶ Nowe yf the woman can not conceaue / the cauſe commynge of ouer muche frigidite and coldeneſſe in the matrice / that ſhall ſhe knowe by theſe tokens: ſhe ſhal feale greate cold about the ſydes / the raynes of the backe and the matrice / her vryne ſhall appeare whyte and thynnyſſhe / and ſometymes alſo ſomewhat ſpyſſe and thycke / and all maner of colde thynges ſhall noye her / hote thyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges ſhall greately comfort her.</p>
               <p>¶ But yf it come by ouer muche humidite of the matrice / that ſhall ſhe knowe by theſe ſygnes: Yf the bodye of her be of a fatte and groſſe diſpoſition / yf with her flowres yſſue forth at the begynnynge and the latterende
<pb n="lxxxiii" facs="tcp:16499:75" rendition="simple:additions"/>of them certayne vyſcous and waterye ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaunce / and that her vrine be whyte / thycke / and ſometyme as it were mylke. Alſoo that ſhe feale greate colde and payne aboute the matrice &amp; pryuie partes / &amp; muche dolour in her ſydes and in the raynes of her backe.</p>
               <p>¶ And when ouer much heate or dryeth in the matrice / is cauſe of the hynderaunce of conception / then is the vryne hye coldred / red or yelowe / beynge thynne with certayne mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes appearyng in the water / the woma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hath greate thyrſte / and bytter ryſynge or belking oute of the ſtomacke in to the mouthe. And manye tymes they that are in this caſe / are verye ſpare and leane in all theyr bodye / ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyng alſo but ſmall quantite of flowres / the whiche thynge maye happen other by ouer muche watche / or ouer much faſtynge / labor / trauell / ſorowe / ſyckeneſſe. &amp;c. But ſuche wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men which naturally are thus ſpare &amp; lene / maye verye hardely be brought to a tempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rancye agayne &amp; be made apte to conceaue. And this ſhalbe ſufficiente for this tyme to knowe whiche qualite by his exceſſe cauſeth ſterilite / nowe wyll we ſhewe howe it ſhalbe knowen whether lacke of conception be in
<pb facs="tcp:16499:76" rendition="simple:additions"/>the woman or elles in the man / and howe to knowe whether the woman be conceaued or no / accordynge to the mynde of ryght expert doctors of phyſycke.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <head>¶ Howe to knowe whether lacke of conception be of the woman or of the man, and howe it maye be perceaued whether ſhe be conceaued or no. ¶ Cap .iiii.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>F ye be deſyrous to know whe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther the man or the woman be hynderance in conception: lette eche of them take of whete and barlye cornes / and of beenes of eche .vii. the which they ſhall ſuffer to be ſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped in theyr ſeueral vryne / the ſpace of .xxiiij. houres / then take .ij. pottes / ſuche as they ſet gylyflowres in / fyll them with good earth / &amp; in the one let be ſet the whete / barlye / &amp; bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes / ſtyped in the mans water / &amp; in the other the whete / barlye / and beanes / ſtyped in the womans water / and euerye mornynge the ſpace of eight or ten dayes / lette eche of them with theyr proper vryne / water the ſayd ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des ſowen in the forenamed pottes / &amp; marke
<pb n="lxxxiiii" facs="tcp:16499:76" rendition="simple:additions"/>whoſe potte dothe proue / &amp; the ſeades therin contained dothe growe / in that partie is not the lacke of conception / but ſee that there come no other water or rayne on the pot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes.</p>
               <p>¶ Ite<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> accordynge to Hypocrates wrytyng yf ye wyl knowe whether the faute be in the woman or no / then lette the woman receaue in to her body vndernethe / beynge well and cloſely cloſed round about the fume of ſome odoriferous perfume / as laudanum / ſtorax / calamyte / lignum aloes / muſke / ambre / and ſuche other / and yf the odour and ſauour of ſuche thynges aſſende thorowe her body vp vnto her noſe / ye ſhall vnderſtande / that ſterilite commeth not of the womans parte / yf not: then is the defecte in her.</p>
               <p>¶ Item yf ſhe take garlycke beynge pylled out of the huſkes / and conueye of it into the pryuie partes / and yf the ſente of it aſſende vp through the bodye vnto the noſe / the wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man is fauteleſſe / yf not: then is there lacke in her. Theſe are ſygnes to knowe whether the lacke be in the man or the woman.</p>
               <p>¶ Whether ſhe be conceaued alreadye or no / ye ſhall knowe by theſe ſygnes: Fyrſte
<pb facs="tcp:16499:77" rendition="simple:additions"/>the flowres yſſue not in ſo great quantite as they are wo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t / but wexe leſſe and leſſe / and in maner nothinge at all commeth from them. Alſo the breſtes begyn to waxe rounder / har<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>der / and ſtyffar then they were wonte to be / the woman ſhall longe after certayne thyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges otherwyſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhe was vſed to do before that tyme. Alſo her vryne waxeth ſpyſſe and thyckyſſhe / by retenſion of the ſuperfluyties. Alſo the woman fealeth her matrice verye faſtelye encloſed and ſhytte / in ſo muche that as Hypocrates ſaythe / the poynte of a nedle maye ſcace enter.</p>
               <p>¶ Item to knowe whether ſhe be concea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned or no / accordynge to Hypocrates mynde / in the .v. of his Ampho. geue vnto the wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man when ſhe is goyng to bedde a quantite of mellicratum to drynke / and yf after that drynke ſhe feale greate payne / gnawing / and tumblynge in her belly / then be ye ſure / that ſhe is conceaued: yf not / ſhe is not co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ceaued / this mellicratum is a drynke made of one parte wyne / an other parte water ſoden to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether / with a quantite of hony.</p>
               <p>¶ But if ye be deſyrous to knowe whether the conception be man or woman: then lette
<pb n="lxxxv" facs="tcp:16499:77" rendition="simple:additions"/>a droppe of her mylke or twayne be mylked on a ſmothe glaſſe / or a bryght knyfe / other elles on the nayle of one of her fyngers / and yf the mylke flewe and ſpredde abrode vpon it / by and by then is it a woman chylde: but yf the droppe of mylke contynue and ſtande ſtyll vppon that / the whiche it is mylked on / then is it ſygne of a man chylde. Item yf it be a male / then ſhall the woman with childe be well coloured / and lyghte in goynge / her belly rounde / bygger towarde the right ſyde then the lefte / for alwayes the man chylde lyeth in the ryghte ſyde / the woman in the lefte ſyde.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <head>¶ Of certayne remedyes and medycynes which ſhall cauſe the woman to conceaue. ¶ Cap .v.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Ll ſterilite then for the moſte parte enſueth and commeth of the dyſtemperancye of one of theſe .iiij. forenamed qualities / wherfore the remedye and cure of the ſame when it chaunſeth / muſt be done by ſuch thynges / the whiche haue contracye power &amp; operation to the exceſſyue qualities
<pb facs="tcp:16499:80" rendition="simple:additions"/>for by that ſhall it be reduced to his tempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rancye agayne.</p>
               <p>¶ As yf that coldeneſſe and moyſteneſſe ex<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ceadynge temperancye in the matrice be oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion of ſterilite / then muſte ſhe applie ſuch thynges to that place / the whiche be of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture hote &amp; drye / the whiche maye calify and warme the place / and alſoo drye vp the yll moyſtenes and humoures contayned in the ſame / hynderynge conception.</p>
               <p>¶ Wherfore take of ſauyne / baytreleues / the flowres of camomell / melylote / maiora<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / caprifolium / herba paralyſis / cytron leues / and ſuch other thynges of aromatycall and hote nature: and ſethe theſe in water to ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther / and let the woman receaue the vapour and fume hereof vndernethe in to her bodye through ſome co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>duite or pype made for that purpoſe: her clothes beynge cloſe about her / that none of the vapour or ayre yſſue oute / &amp; ouer this let her ſyt all a nyght / yf ſhe may / receauyng euer the fume hereof in to her bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dye / and in the mornynge let her accompany with her huſbande / and ſhe ſhall conceaue.</p>
               <p>¶ A bathe alſo for the ſame purpoſe: when the tyme of her flowres aboute the ende of
<pb n="lxxxvi" facs="tcp:16499:78" rendition="simple:additions"/>the laſte quartar of the moone is almoſte fy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyſhed: let her bathe herſelf in a bathe / wher in is decocte &amp; ſoden caprifolium / malowes / frenche malowes / holyoke / rooſes / iunyper beryes / parytarye / wylde myntes / bay leues / myrtylles / ſauyne / camomell / pynpernell / myntes / maioram / cytron leues / baſyll / peny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryall / and ſuche other. But before that ſhe bathe her in this water / it ſhalbe beſt for her to be purged and clenſed from the colde hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours with theodoricon / or with benedicta / or with the pylles which be called ſinequibꝰ eſſe nolo / to be had at the apothecaryes / and then let her enter in to this foreſayde bathe / and when ſhe commeth forthe of the bathe agayne / then let her take of diamargariton / or of muſcata / to the qua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tite of a nutte / dryn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kynge it with good and odoriferous or well ſinellynge wyne / other elles let her take of this electuarye folowynge / whiche is verye excellent for that purpoſe.</p>
               <p>¶ Take of ſpyke / nuttemegges / cloues / ze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doarium / galyngale / longe peper / drye roſes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtorax / alipta muſcata / of eche of theſe lyke muche / then take of the roote of tormentyll as muche as of all the other forenamed thin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ges
<pb facs="tcp:16499:79" rendition="simple:additions"/>to gether / and beate all theſe to pouder / temperynge them with a ſufficiente qua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tite of clarifyed honye / to the whiche alſo adde a lyttell of pure muſke. Of this electuarium bothe euenynge and mornynge the ſpace of ten dayes let the woman take to the moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenaunce of a nutte with good odoryferous wyne bathynge her ſelfe alſo euery daye the ſpace of the ſayde ten dayes: at her comynge forthe of the bathe / receauyng of the foreſaid electuarye / then alſo let her perfume her pry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uities with the ſauoure and fume of lauda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num / frankencenſe / xiloaloes / ſtorax / ambre / alipta / xilobalſamum / and ſuche other thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges. And after this let her make a ſuppoſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarye annoynted with magna trifera / or eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dra / with the pouder of olibanum / and the dyle of bays myxte and tempered to gether / and let her retayne this ſuppoſytarye in her pryuities all the day tyme the foreſayd ſpace of ten dayes / and then at the ten dayes ende (the man and woman accompanynge toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther) god wyllynge / ſhe ſhalbe conceaued / &amp; theſe be the remedyes yf the defecte &amp; lacke of conception come by reaſon of coldeneſſe and moyſteneſſe.</p>
               <pb n="lxxxvii" facs="tcp:16499:79" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <p>¶ But yf it come by diſtemperaunce of the matrice in hote and drye / fyrſte lette the hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour which is cauſe of it / be purged by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neniente medycynes / &amp; then euery nyght the ſpace of ten dayes let her bathe herſelfe in warme water / nothing elles beyng put vnto it / &amp; in this batthe let her remayne not long / and at her co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>minge forth geue her to drynke of trifera magna / with watered wyne / and after this receaue ſhe the vapoure &amp; fume of the decoction of theſe herbes vnderneth in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to her priuy partes: take violettes / beerefote / parytarye / and penyryall / ſethe them in wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter: and then conuaye in to the ſame place a ſuppoſytary of trifera magna with the pou<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>der of olibanum.</p>
               <p>¶ Item a ſuppoſitarye whiche is wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full good in expellynge and dowyng awaye ſuche thynges whiche let conception: take of ſiler montanum beaten to pouder .ij. dram<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s / of the renatte of an hare the .iiij. parte of a dram<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / and temper theſe to gether with clari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyed honye and the oyle of bayes / &amp; annoynt here with a ſuppoſytarye / the whiche let the woman retayne in her ſecreates the ſpace of a daye and a nyght.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:16499:78" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <p>¶ Ite<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a ſuppoſytary made of hares dunge and hony tempered to gether / is verye excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent for the ſame purpoſe / but let the woma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> abſtayne from all maner of ſalte and ſharpe meates / and vſe to drynke good odoriferous and pleaſaunt wynes alayd with water.</p>
               <p>¶ Alſo to drynke of the wyne in whiche is diſſolued muſke / or elles viſcus quercinus / is good to helpe to conception / alſo the herte bone of an herte / and the ſcrapynge of yuery is very good for the ſame.</p>
               <p>¶ Item a ſuppoſytary for the ſame / which hathe ben many tymes well proued for that purpoſe: Take garlycke pylled and clenſed frome the huſkes / and ſethe it in the oyle of rooſes / or elles the oyle of maioram vnto the tyme that it be dyſſolued / and that all the moyſtenes be departed from it / then take it out of the oyle agayne / and ſtampe it / &amp; then wrappe it in wooll / and conuaye it ſuppoſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarywyſe in to the pryuie partes / and there keape it the ſpace of a daye: this thynge is maruelous good for conception / and hathe ben well proued.</p>
               <p>¶ Dyuers other lettes of conception and remedyes for the ſame myght here haue ben
<pb n="lxxxviii" facs="tcp:16499:80" rendition="simple:additions"/>declared / whiche for breuite and ſhorteneſſe we for this tyme do let paſſe / makynge here an ende of this treatyſe / the whiche we haue compoſed and tranſlated oute of Laten / to the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of God / the vti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lite and profette of all honeſte ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trones.</p>
            </div>
            <closer>Deo gratias.</closer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>¶ Imprynted at London / by. T. R.</p>
            <p>Anno Domini. M.CCCCC.XL.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
